<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chelys, minuritionum artificio exornata, sive, Minuritiones ad  basin, etiam ex tempore modulandi ratio in tres partes distributa = The division-viol, or, The art of playing ex tempore upon a  ground, divided into three parts ... / authore Christophoro Simpson.</title>
            <title>Division-violist. Latin &amp; English</title>
            <author>Simpson, Christopher, d. 1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3809B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11994947</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11994947</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52084</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52084)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 824:4 and 1101:3 or 2098:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Chelys, minuritionum artificio exornata, sive, Minuritiones ad  basin, etiam ex tempore modulandi ratio in tres partes distributa = The division-viol, or, The art of playing ex tempore upon a  ground, divided into three parts ... / authore Christophoro Simpson.</title>
                  <title>Division-violist. Latin &amp; English</title>
                  <author>Simpson, Christopher, d. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Editio secunda.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[12], 61, [1], 53-67 p., [2] leaves of plates : ill., port., music.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Latin and English in parallel columns.</note>
                  <note>First ed. published in 1659 under title: The division-violinist.</note>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>Includes engraved frontispiece portrait of Christopher Simpson.</note>
                  <note>Duplicate copies appear on reels 824 and 1101.</note>
                  <note>Wing number S3809A cancelled in Wing (CD-ROM, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. Of the viol itself, with instructions to play upon it -- II. Use of the concords, or a compendium of descant -- III. The method of ordering division to a ground.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Viols --  Instruction and study --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thorough bass --  Instruction and study.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Christophori Simpson Effigies.</head>
                  <byline>J. Carwardon pinxit.</byline>
                  <byline>Guil. Faithorne sculp:</byline>
                  <q>NEQUE LUX SINE VMBRA</q>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Christopher Simpson</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHELYS, MINURITIONUM ARTIFICIO EXORNATA: <hi>SIVE, Minuritiones ad Baſin, etiam Ex tempore Modulandi Ratio.</hi> IN TRES PARTES DISTRIBUTA.</p>
            <p>The Diviſion-Viol, OR, The Art of PLAYING <hi>Ex tempore</hi> upon a GROUND. <hi>DIVIDED INTO THREE PARTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Pars I. <hi>Chelyos tractandae Praecepta.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pars II. <hi>Melotheſiae Compendium.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pars III. <hi>Minuritiones ad Baſin aptan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Methodus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>Part I. <hi>Of the Viol it ſelf, with Inſtructions to Play upon it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Part II. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Concords, or a Compendium of Deſcant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Part III. <hi>The Method of ordering Diviſion to a Ground.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Authore CHRISTOPHORO SIMPSON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDITIO SEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Godbid</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane.</hi> M.DC.LXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS EVER HONOURED PATRON Sir IOHN BOLLES Bar<hi rend="sup">t.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe, upon the firſt Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was Dedicated to your late Father, and not without good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for, all the Motives that could enter into a Dedication of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, did oblige me to it. Firſt, as he was a moſt eminent Patron of <hi>Muſick,</hi> and <hi>Muſitians.</hi> Secondly, as he was not only a Lover of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> but alſo a great Performer in it. Thirdly, as the ſaid Treatiſe had its Conception, Birth, and Accompliſhment under His Roof, in your Minority. Laſtly, as he was my peculiar Patron; affording me a cheerful Maintenance, when the Iniquity of the Times had reduced me (with many others in that common calamity) to a condition of needing it.</p>
            <p>That Impreſſion being ſpent, and another importun'd, this Second comes now in order to kiſs Your Hands, and deſire Your Patronage, as Immediate Heir and Succeſſor to your Father; not only to his Eſtate, but likewiſe to his Dignity, Worth and Virtue. And in This <hi>Dedication</hi> I have ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which I had not in the Former. One is, that <hi>you</hi> were the chief occaſion of this Book; and therefore, if there be any thing of worth in it, the World may thank You for it: For, it was contriv'd and carried on for Your Inſtruction in <hi>Muſick,</hi> at ſuch vacant hours as you were not imploy'd in Studies of more concernment: And, as it was made for You, ſo it has made You (by your ingenuity) not only the greateſt Artiſt, but alſo the ableſt Judge of it, that (I think) is this day in <hi>Europe;</hi> (I mean) of a Gentleman, and no Profeſſor of the <hi>Science.</hi> And this opinion of mine I find confirmed by a Paper of Verſes printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> when you
<pb facs="tcp:52084:3"/>travell'd thoſe Parts, which were occaſion'd by your rare Expreſſions on the <hi>Viol</hi> at a <hi>Muſick-meeting;</hi> in which were preſent not only divers Grandees of that Court and City, with ſome Ambaſſadors of Foreign States; but alſo the Great <hi>Muſitians</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who are eſteem'd Superlative; all admiring your Knowledge in <hi>Muſick,</hi> and your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency upon that <hi>Inſtrument.</hi> That I might give Your ſelf, our Nation, and the Author of thoſe Verſes the Right which is due to each, I have preſumed to Reprint them on the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Page, as well for a Juſtification of what I have ſaid, as alſo for an Encouragement to thoſe who ſhall make uſe of the ſame Inſtructions which guided you on to that Perfection. I am loth to detain you too long, yet one thing I muſt acquaint you with, which is, That our <hi>Diviſion-Viol</hi> Sounds better now in <hi>Latin</hi> than it formerly did in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that hath improv'd it is your kind Acquaintance, my ever honoured Friend (and ſometime Scholar in <hi>Muſick</hi>) Mr. <hi>William Marſh,</hi> that it might be underſtood in Foreign Parts; and I have cauſed its Native Language to be joyned therewith, to make it uſeful at Home as well as Abroad. This is all I have to ſay, more than what I ſuppoſe you already know; which is, that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt real and Humble Servant <hi>Chr. Simpſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:3"/>
            <head>EXIMIAE NOBILITATI, DOCTRINAE, VIRTUTI cum ſumma Muſices harmonia conſono adoleſcenti, ILLUSTRISSIMO DOMINO, D. IOANNI BOLLES, ANGLO, ROBERTI BARONET. HAEREDI FILIO.</head>
            <p>Mirificam ſuavitatem ejuſdem &amp; argutiam in tangenda Britanica Chely, quam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgò dicunt <hi>VIOLAM MAJOREM</hi> ſtupori Romae fuiſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>ODE JACOBI ALBANI GHIBBESII, MED. DOCT. AC IN ROMANA SAPIENTIA ELOQ. PROF. PRIMARII.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>RES ſuas dicam ſibi habere Phoebo,</l>
               <l>Te modis aures retinente noſtras:</l>
               <l>Quale ſolamen Samius negârit</l>
               <l>Doctor Olympo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quantus Alcides animos triumphas,</l>
               <l>Gallico major! trahat ille vulgus:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roma Te</hi> vidit ſtupefacta primos</l>
               <l>Ducere patres;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Roma tormentum fidium inſecuta</l>
               <l>Dulce, concentus licèt ipſa mater.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Allobrox</hi> mirae <hi>Venetúſque</hi> plauſit</l>
               <l>Nuntius arti.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vividum claro, celebrémque alumno</l>
               <l>Laudo <hi>Simpſonum:</hi> vaga fama quantum</l>
               <l>Theſſali cultu juvenis magiſtrum</l>
               <l>Diſtulit orbi.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hactenùs plectrum, citharámque vates</l>
               <l>Noverint; <hi>Arcu Violáque</hi> freti</l>
               <l>Concinent poſthac: nequè Threſſa certet</l>
               <l>Chorda <hi>Britannae.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O virûm felix, &amp; opima rerum</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Albion,</hi> ſedes placitura Muſis!</l>
               <l>O poli ſidus mihi, quò remotam</l>
               <l>Dirigo puppim!</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <hi>Monumentum, &amp; pignus amoris.</hi>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>à Muſaeo noſtro,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Kal. April.</hi> 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>ROMAE, Excudebat Franciſcus Moneta. MDCLXI.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Superiorum permiſſu.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Roger L'Estrange" type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Came with great willingneſs (though under the Obligation likewiſe of a Duty) to the reading of this Book; out of a Reſpect both to the <hi>Author,</hi> and to the <hi>Subject</hi> of it: the <hi>One</hi> being my Familiar <hi>Friend,</hi> and the <hi>Other,</hi> my Singular <hi>Entertaynment,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</hi> Having now thoroughly, and carefully peruſed it, I ſhould reckon my ſelf a little wanting to the Publique, if I acquainted not the world, that in ſo doing I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived much Benefit and Satisfaction. It bears for Title, <hi>THE DIVISION VIOL; or, The Art of Playing Extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore upon a Ground;</hi> and it does certainly anſwer That pretence, both for <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Method,</hi> to the higheſt point of reaſonable Expectation. And yet I cannot ſo properly call it the <hi>Beſt,</hi> as (indeed,) the <hi>only Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> I find extant upon this Argument; which without doubt renders it the more valuable, in that it is brought upon the firſt eſſay ſo near to perfection: for it is a piece ſo Inſtructive, and of ſuch a Latitude, that it meets all Capacities, and finds no man either too wiſe, or too weak to be the better for it. Briefly; As to the Command, and Maſtery of the Viol, (in that point which is the Excellency of That Inſtrument) either for Hand, or Skill, I will take upon me to aver, that whoever has This Book by him, has one of the beſt Tutors in the world at his Elbow. And let me add, that although it be Calculated eſpecially (as appears by the Title) for the <hi>Diviſion Viol,</hi> yet when you come to the Deſcant, and Directions for Diminution upon a Ground, you will find it a work of exceeding uſe in all ſorts of Muſick whatſoever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_music_lover">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:4"/>
            <head>Ad Muſices Amatorem.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>A rerum humanarum conditio eſt, ut dùm explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur, dùm ad vivum reſecantur, Nihili nos ſui, unde primùm emerſerunt, admoneant. Scientias Arteſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quarum ſtupendos progreſſus nemo non videt, ac Diſciplinas praeſertim Mathematicas ſi ad Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipia prima, ad Axiomata ac Poſtulata revoces, res nihili putes, mireriſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſubitò tam exiguis è fontibus tantum prodigiorum conflux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe Oceanum. Plurima iſtius generis è minimis initiis exiſtunt maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Elucet prae caeteris in Muſicâ eximia quaedam ab exordio tenui claritudo. Eam ſi temerè ipſo in limine intuearis, humilis inprimis, nullo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ornamento ſpectabilis, intus canere videtur omnia; in penitiori Harmonia Sacrario illuſtris apparet admodùm at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> de debellatis ſaepiùs Auditorum animis erecto ſublimè tropaeo, victrix ac triumphabunda feſtivum Paeana ingeminat. Niſi forte illud Poetae ei rectiùs convenit:
<q>
                  <l>Parva ortu primo, mox ſeſe attollit in auras,</l>
                  <l>Ingreditur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolo, &amp; caput inter nubila condit.</l>
               </q> Ne longiùs abeam, vel hanc ipſam Chelyn Minuritionum artificio exornatum conſule. Praecepta quae in aditu primùm occurrunt, exilia forſam ac tenuia cenſeas; inde tamen ſi filum texueris, quo errabunda veſtigia pedetentim caute<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> regas, difficili te Labyrintho ſenſim expedies, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in apertis demùm amoeniſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Minuritionum campis, magno cum foenore ac liquidiſſimo voluptatis ſenſu ſpatiari demiraberis. Teſtantur id ii, quorum ex hiſce elementis inſignis prognata modulandi ſolertia incredibiles paſſim animorum motus plauſuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> excitavit. Quare viſum eſt Chelyn hanc Anglicam latio donare ac publici juris facere, ne res communibus votis tantopere expetita, Inſulâ dumtaxat vnâ circumſcriberetur; at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ut, quò praevia jampridem pervolavit fama quantâ cum venuſtate ac arte Chelys in Angliâ tractari ſoleat, Ars quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ipſa transfretaret.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="glossary_of_technical_terms">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:5"/>
            <head>Nomenclatura quarundam vocum in gratiam Tyronum variè reddita.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Anglicè.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Gallicè.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Italicè.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chelys.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Viol.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ne Viole.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Viola.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbo.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Belly of the Viol.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Table.</cell>
                     <cell>La Tauola.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tergum.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Back.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le fond.</cell>
                     <cell>Il fondo.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Jugum.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Neck.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le Manche.</cell>
                     <cell>Il manico.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Canon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Fingerboard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Touche.</cell>
                     <cell>La Tartiera.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chordotomus. Magas ſuperior, crenae ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riores.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Nut of the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerboard.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le Cillet.</cell>
                     <cell>Il Capitaſto.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Intervalla; ligulae.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Frets.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Les Touches.</cell>
                     <cell>J Taſti.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Collabi.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Pegs.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Les Cheuilles.</cell>
                     <cell>J Piroli, Biſcheri.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Magas inſerior; Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulus.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Bridge.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le Cheualet.</cell>
                     <cell>Il Ponticello.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Retinaculum; Cauda.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Tail-piece.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Queiie.</cell>
                     <cell>La Coda.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Suſtentaculum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinum.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Sound-Poſt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>L' Ame.</cell>
                     <cell>L' Anima.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Arcus; Plectrum.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Bow.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>L' Archet.</cell>
                     <cell>L' Arco.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Setae.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The hairs of the bow</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Les Creins.</cell>
                     <cell>J crini.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iſthmus. Aſſerculus ſetis obſtans.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Nut of the Bow.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Hauſte.</cell>
                     <cell>La Alza.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sex fides chordae.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Six ſtrings.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Les ſix Chordes.</cell>
                     <cell>Le Sei chorde.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Suprema. Secunda.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Treble. The Second.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Chanterelle la Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde.</cell>
                     <cell>Il Cantino, la Seconda.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tertia. Quarta.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Third. The Fourth.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Troiſieſme, la Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieſme.</cell>
                     <cell>La Terza, La Quarta.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Quinta. Sexta. ſeu ima.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Fifth. The Sixth.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La cinquieſme, La Sixieſme.</cell>
                     <cell>La Quinta, La Seſta.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tonus.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Key of a Song.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le Ton d' vn chant.</cell>
                     <cell>Il Tuono d' vn Canto.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clavis.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Cliff.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>La Clef.</cell>
                     <cell>La Chiaue.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>B. Molle.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Flat.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le B. Mol.</cell>
                     <cell>Il B. Molle.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>B. durum, quadratum.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Sharp.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Le B. Quarre.</cell>
                     <cell>Il B. quadro.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Notae</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Notes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Les Nottes.</cell>
                     <cell>Le Note.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Brevis. 𝆸</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Brief.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Breve.</cell>
                     <cell>Breve.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Semibrevis. 𝆹</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Semibrief.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Semibreve.</cell>
                     <cell>Semibreve.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Minima. 톹텥</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Minim.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Minime.</cell>
                     <cell>Minima.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Semiminima, 톺텥</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Crochet.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Noire.</cell>
                     <cell>Simini-nima.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fuſe, chroma. 톼텮</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quaver.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Crochiie.</cell>
                     <cell>Croma.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Semifuſa, Semichro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. 톼텯</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Semiquaver.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Double Crochiie.</cell>
                     <cell>Semicroma.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Semifuſae Semis. <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:notedemisemiquaver"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>demisemiquaver note</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Demi-Semiquaver.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Triple Crochiie.</cell>
                     <cell>Arbiſcroma.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Contrapunctus.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Counterpoint.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Contrepoint. Notte contre Notte.</cell>
                     <cell>Contrapunto. Nota contra Nota.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Contrapunctus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporalis.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deſcant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Contrepoint a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miere veiie.</cell>
                     <cell>Contrapunto a mente.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Syncope, Ligatura.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Binding or Ligature.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ne Liaiſon.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Legatura.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ptôſis. Cadentia.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Cadence.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ne Cadence.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Cadenza.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Teretiſmi.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Double Relliſhes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Des Cadences de noeuds et tremble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens.</cell>
                     <cell>Cadenze di Groppoe Trillo.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clauſula finalis.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cloſe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Cadence finale.</cell>
                     <cell>Cadenza finale.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:52084:5"/>
               <head>Elenchus eorum quae hoc libro Continentur.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>Parte Primâ.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>CHelyos tractandae Praecepta. <hi>pag. 1.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Chely ipſâ, qualis Minuritioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus maximè quadret, &amp; quomodo concinnanda. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Plectro, ſeu Arcu Muſico. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Collocatione Chelyos. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quomodo tenendus &amp; movendus Arcus. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Siniſtrae Collocatione, motuque. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Chelyos Chordotoniâ ad Scalam Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicam accommodatâ. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quâ ratione eaedem Notae in diverſis Chordis exprimi poſſint. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quare Digiti ſiniſtrae in eâdem ſaepè ſede continuandi ſint. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Regula movendi Arcum. <hi>p. 6.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quo ordine Digiti Canoni applicandi ſint. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quis motus Brachio dextro, manuſque juncturae conveniat. <hi>p 7.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quomodo plures ſimul notae perſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendae ſint. <hi>p. 9.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Triplis. <hi>p. 10.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De ſonorum blanditiis at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Leporibus. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Lepôres ex tremoribus oriundi. <hi>p. 11.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>Parte Secundâ.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>MElotheſiae Compendium. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Intervallis. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Concordantiis. <hi>p. 15.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tranſitio Concordantiarum. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Melotheſiae Clavi ſeu Tono. <hi>p. 16.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:52084:6"/>
                     <item>Quâ ratione Baſſus conformádus ſit. <hi>p 17</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quo pacto Cantus Baſſo adſtruendus ſit. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Triphoniis. <hi>p. 18.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Tetraphoniis. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Sexia. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quis Diſcordantiis locus ſit. <hi>p. 20.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Tritono, &amp; Semidiapente. <hi>p. 22.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Contemplatio Concordantiarum Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caram. <hi>p. 23.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Muſicarum Concordantiarum Analogia ad Planetarum aſpectus. <hi>p. 24.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>Parte Tertiâ.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>â ratione Minuritiones ad Baſin aptandae ſint. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritionum genera. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritio Fundamentalis. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritio Melothetica. <hi>p. 35.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritio Mixta. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cadentiarum duo genera. <hi>p. 37.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Quintis &amp; Octavis in Minuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. <hi>p. 42.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Sextis &amp; Tertiis in Minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritione. <hi>p. 44.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Semiminimis. <hi>p. 46.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Fuſis. <hi>p. 50.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De <hi>b</hi> Molli &amp; Duro. <hi>p. 52.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritionum Syntaxis. <hi>p. 56.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>De Baſi Continua. <hi>p. 57.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritiones ſingulari Chely quâ ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione aptandae. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Quâ Methodo duae Cheles Baſi alludere debent. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minuritiones plurium Partium Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi ratio. <hi>p. 59.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:52084:5"/>
               <head>The Contents of the Book.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>In the Firſt Part.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>OF the Viol it ſelf, with Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons how to play upon it. <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>§ 2. What kind of Viol is fitteſt for Diviſion, and how to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 3. What kind of Bow. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</item>
                     <item>§ 4. How to hold or place the Viol. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 5. How to hold and move the Bow. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 6. The poſture of the Left Hand. <hi>p.</hi> 4.</item>
                     <item>§ 7. How the Viol is Tuned, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the Scale of Muſick. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 8. How the ſame Notes may be play'd upon different Strings. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 9. A Rule for Holding on the Fingers. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</item>
                     <item>§ 10. A Rule for the Motion of the Bow. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</item>
                     <item>§ 11. Of ordering the fingers in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Notes. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 12. The Motion of the Right Arm and Wriſt. <hi>p.</hi> 7.</item>
                     <item>§ 13. How to order the Bow in double Stops. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</item>
                     <item>§ 14. Of Tripla's. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</item>
                     <item>§ 15. Concerning the Gracing of Notes. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 16. Shaked Graces. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>In the Second Part.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>§ 1. USe of the Concords, or a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium of Deſcant. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</item>
                     <item>§ 2. Of Intervalls. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 3. Of the Concords. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</item>
                     <item>§ 4. Paſſage of the Concords. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 5. Concerning the Key or Tone. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:52084:6"/>
                     <item>§ 6. How to frame a Baſs. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</item>
                     <item>§ 7. How to joyn a Treble to the Baſs. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 8. Compoſition of three Parts. <hi>p.</hi> 18.</item>
                     <item>§ 9. Compoſition of four Parts. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 10. Concerning a Sixth. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</item>
                     <item>§ 11. Uſe of Diſcords. <hi>p.</hi> 20.</item>
                     <item>§ 12. Of the exceſſive Fourth, and Defective Fifth. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</item>
                     <item>§ 13. Reflections upon the Concords of Muſick. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</item>
                     <item>§ 14. The Analogy of Muſical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords to the Aſpects of the Planets. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>In the third Part.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>§ 1. OF Diviſion, and the manner of performing it. <hi>p.</hi> 27.</item>
                     <item>§ 2. Several kinds of Diviſion. <hi>p.</hi> 28.</item>
                     <item>§ 3. Breaking the Ground. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 4. Deſcant Diviſion. <hi>p.</hi> 35.</item>
                     <item>§ 5. Mixt Diviſion. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</item>
                     <item>§ 6. Cadences of two ſorts. <hi>p.</hi> 37.</item>
                     <item>§ 7. Concerning Fifths and Eighths in Diviſion. <hi>p.</hi> 42</item>
                     <item>§ 8. Concerning Sixths and Thirds in Diviſion. <hi>p.</hi> 44.</item>
                     <item>§ 9. Of Crochets. <hi>p.</hi> 46.</item>
                     <item>§ 10. Of Quavers. <hi>p.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>§ 11. Of <hi>b</hi> Flat and Sharp. <hi>p.</hi> 52.</item>
                     <item>§ 12. Concerning the ordering of Diviſion. <hi>p.</hi> 56.</item>
                     <item>§ 13. Of a Continued Ground. <hi>p.</hi> 57.</item>
                     <item>§ 14. Of Compoſing Diviſion for one Viol to a Ground. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 15. Of two Viols playing together <hi>ex tempore</hi> to a Ground. <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ 16. Of Compoſing Diviſions of Two or Three parts. <hi>p.</hi> 59.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="license_to_reprint">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Let this Book, Intituled,</hi> THE DIVISION-VIOL, be Reprinted,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>September</hi> 24. 1665.</date>
               <signed>ROGER L'ESTRANGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:7"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Forma Chelyos utravis Minuritonibus apta, ſed Prima reſonantior.</head>
                  <figDesc>two division-viols in different forms</figDesc>
                  <head type="sub">The Figure or Shape of a Diviſion-Viol may be either of theſe; but the Firſt is better for Sound.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52084:7"/>
               <head>CHELYS, Minuritionum Artificio Exornata.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>PARS PRIMA. Chelyos tractandae Praecepta.</head>
                  <p>CHELYS peritum nacta Fidicinem, cum caeteris Inſtrumentis Muſicis de palmâ certare jure meritò poteſt. De ejus inprimis agendum Conſtructione, tum de Tangendi Modo. Libandum praeterea aliquid de Conſonantiis Muſicis; ut ad Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuritiones, quae Chelyn ornant commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantque maximè, gradatim aſcendatur.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Chely ipsâ, qualis Minuritionibus maximè quadret, &amp; quomodo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnanda.</head>
                     <p>CHelyn quae Minuritionibus deſtinatur, breviorem eſſe convenit eâ, quae Choro muſico inſervit; ut faciliori negotio ſtringi percurrique poſſit: quâ in re, manuum digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torumque, ut quiſque arctioribus vel largio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus eſt, habenda ratio. Magnitudo ut plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimùm ejuſmodi ſit, quae Fidem duorum pedum &amp; ſemiſſis à Magade inferiori ſeu ponticulo ad Chordotomum ſeu crenas ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periores admittat. Sonus, ſit tinnulus &amp; excitatus, qualis fere eſſe ſolet minorum Chelyum ſeu Violinorum. Eum videlicet ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num nanciſcuntur ſimili figurâ majores, quarum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terus ex ſolido trunco, Lintris inſtar, excavatur.</p>
                     <p>Hexachordam eſſe oportet; annexis ſeptem Ligulis, aliquanto craſſioribus iis, quae Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtudinis collum ambiunt. Quâ verò ſede ad Fidem apertam Octava ſuperius in Canone ſive manubrio reſonat, ligulam extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam figere opportunum erit, quae digitos iſthac oberrantes veluti familiare ſignum ad moneat, quâ intercapedine vicina deinceps intervalla ratâ proportione pertentanda ſint.</p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52084:8"/>
                     <p>Fides item ſint paullò craſſiores Chordis Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae-Chelyos, aequali diſcrimine Canoni ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extenſae, ut faciliùs aptiuſque premantur.</p>
                     <p>Ponticulus ita arcuetur, ut Chordae ſingulae diſtinctè fidentique plectro abſque ullâ anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vibrari queant.</p>
                     <p>Canon ſit laevis &amp; aequabilis. Ejus longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo duas tertias partes ſpatii occupet, quod inter ponticulum ſuperioremque Chordoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum interjacet. Ponticulum declivi utrim<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> flexu aemuletur; ut chordae ſingulae manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio, quemadmodum dictum eſt, aequaliter ſuperemineant. Si Ponticuli curvatura fuerit ut Arcus <hi>A. B.</hi> Canonis ima pars ſit ut <hi>C. D.</hi> ſumma, ut <hi>E. F.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Haec Chelyum fabris propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Plectro ſeu Arcu Muſico.</head>
                     <p>PLectri Arcus rigidus ſit, mediocri pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere: Setae ad duos pedes quadrantemque tenſae, aſſerculo haud oblongo, ad digiti latitudinem aut paullò altiùs, attollantur; qui quaſi Iſthmus ſetas ab Arcu diſtineat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Collocatione Chelyos.</head>
                     <p>UBI te aptâ in ſede collocaveris, Chelyn utroque genu decenter complectere, ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que pars ima ſuris utrimque innitatur. Pedes tantillum divaricati ſolo firmiter inſiſtant. Chelys ſumma ad ſiniſtrum humerum leniter proclinet; ut eo ſitu, etiam nullo manus fulcimento perſiſtat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quomodo tenendus et movendus Arcus.</head>
                     <p>A Prehendatur Arcus prope Iſthmum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremo pollice duobuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> primoribus digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; ita ut Pollex &amp; Index caudicem teneant, alter<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> digitus parumper inſtexus ſetis oblu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetur: eo pacto nimirum librabitur arcus, ne ſlaccidus ad extremum pendeat. Adhiberi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt &amp; annularis, ſi ejus ope caeteri indigeant; quamvis ad minuritiones id minuùs conveniat.</p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52084:8"/>
                     <p>Extento fidenter brachio, Fides haud pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul à ponticulo ſigillatim liquidéque vibren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, genibus ne fortè offendiculo ſint, cautè reductis.</p>
                     <figure/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52084:9"/>
                     <head>De Siniſtrae Collocatione, Motuque.</head>
                     <p>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gum Chelyos ne manu conſtringe, ut in Violinis fit; ſed ut in Teſtudine Pollicem averſo Manubrio ita applica, ut Indici in adverſo Canone ſe moventi plerumque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeat. Hinc faciliori negotio manus pro re natâ in omnem partem perlabetur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Chelyos Chordotoniâ ad Scalam Muſicam accommodatâ.</head>
                     <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ilibet ferè Muſicae candidatus Scalam Guidonianam callere ſolet; quâ probè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectâ, Chelyos attemperatio ſeu Chordotonia adjectae Tabellae ope facilè adornabitur. Infima ſiquidem Semibrevis dabit tonum infimae Chordae in <hi>D.</hi> unde caeterarum diſcrimen ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metur in <hi>G. C. E. A. D.</hi> Reliquos tonos ſupra <hi>D.</hi> aſſequêris, ſi Chordam ſupremam per intervalla quae Ligulis deſignantur, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulum verſus gradatim preſſeris.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Attemperatâ jam Chely, reliquos ſonos ſeu notas ſurſum deorſumque modulari ſi velis, quibus id digitis perficias adjecti monent nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meri, <hi>1, 2, 3, 4; 1</hi> Indicem ſignat, <hi>2</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, <hi>3</hi> Annularem <hi>4</hi> Minimum.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quâ ratione eaedem Notae in diverſis Chordis exprimi poſſint.</head>
                     <p>ANimadvertendum porro eſt, earundem Notarum ſonos, qui vel apertis Chordis, vel per conſuetos ligularum gradus exprimun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, commodiore digitorum applicatione in ſuperioribus ligulis, atque alienâ ſaepe in Chordâ elici; uti videre eſt iis in notis quibus appoſitus eſt Aſteriſcus: Earum nempe ſonus, tametſi paulò ante in ſupremâ Chordâ expreſſus fuerit, in alterâ tamen Strophâ, preſſis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundae
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52084:9"/>chordae ligulis, perinde ut in primâ conſequitur: Quod tuo ipſe Marte, dum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitorum commodo ſtudes, identidem tentando explorabis.</p>
                     <p>Ex plurimis Scalae Muſicae lineis, quinque tantummodo in uſum Chelyos aſſumuntur, cumque in Melodiae decurſu Nota aliqua Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadem evaſerit, appoſitâ clavi alterâ, ad alteram ſimiliter Pentadem reducitur.</p>
                     <p>In proximo Paradigmate operae pretium feceris, ſi manum ſenſim exerceas, nec niſi lentè admodum feſtines, id imprimis ſtudens, ut ſuus cuique Notae ſonus, liquidus plenuſque conſtet: quod fiet, ſi chordas extremis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninò digitis conſtanter ac validè premas; tum Arcu, quantus quantus eſt, rurſum prorſum ducto ſingulas chromas diſtinctè ad plenum evibres.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quare Digiti ſiniſtrae in eâdem ſaepè ſede continuandi ſint.</head>
                     <p>SIquem ligulis digitum appreſſeris, eum, dum reliquis digitis caetera exequeris, nè prius attolle quàm id alia occaſio poſtulet; quo pacto, aequabiliori digitorum decurſui conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, abſque hiulco incertoque tripudio, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numque etiam ſublato arcu continuabis. Ejus morae ſignum <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:direct"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>direct</ex>
                        </expan>
; ab eâ notâ cui digitum immorari oportet, ad eam uſque extenditur, quâ vibratâ ſuſtolli poteſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52084:10"/>
                     <head>Regula movendi Arcum.</head>
                     <p>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m numerum chromarum vel ſemichro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum parem obſervaveris, ut <hi>2, 4, 6, 8.</hi> Prorſum movendus eſt Arcus, tametſi in praecedenti Notâ conſimili motu adactus fuerit; Quòd ſi numerum imparem deprehenderis, ut <hi>3, 5, 7;</hi> quod ferè ob Notam puncto auctam, aut pauſas impares contingit, retrorſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocandus eſt; quamvis id ſubinde exceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem patiatur, Cujus rei exemplum ſub cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Paradigmatis <hi>5</hi> reperies.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quo ordine Digiti Canoni applicandi ſint.</head>
                     <p>SIquando Minuritio ad extremas ligulas aut etiam ulteriùs proceſſerit, Suprema Nota tertio aut quarto digito premitur: Si tertio, primus &amp; ſecundus in proximis Notis aſcendentibus vel deſcendentibus ordine ſuo occupantur: Si Nota ſuprema quartum digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſeu Minimum vendicârit, Nota proxima ſi dura fuerit, tertium; ſi mollis, ſecundum poſtulabit. Id verò certo certius ſtatues, ſive tertium ſive quartum ſuprema Nota diſtineat, Tertiam inferiorem Indice premendam eſſe, unde ad caeteras Notas auſpicandus eſt tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Quod ſi binas notas proximè ſibi ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes eidem digito aſſignatas repereris, id propterea fit, ut digiti ad praedictam Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxin diſponantur, vel ut conſimilis poſiturae digitorum in alteram ſedem transferatur. Obſervandum tamen Minimo digito rarius locum eſſe verſus Ponticulum, ubi interſtitia tonorum ac Semitonorum contractiora ſunt, quàm inter ligulas ubi majori diſſident inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallo.</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52084:10"/>
                     <p>Quo porro ordine de Chordâ in Chordam digiti movendi ſint, ſuâ quiſque induſtriâ facilè indagabit, dùm eorum expeditiori progreſſui conſulit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quis motus Brachio dextro, Manuſque juncturae conveniat.</head>
                     <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>od ad Brachii motum attinet; quamvis humeri juncturam movere ſaepenumero ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſit tardioribus in Notis, in celerioribus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vix id fieri poterit abſque totius corporis indecorâ ſuccuſſatione. Quare ad notas bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viores non niſi Junctura manus moveri ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tento rigidè brachio ut plurimùm debet, in aequabili praeſertim minuritione; id<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem corporis compoſitionem Tyronibus maximè commendatur. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi tamen minuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio hinc inde ſubſultat, aut non admodùm properat, cubiti motum cum manus Juncturâ una conſpirare opus eſt. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t arcus pro impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio gubernetur, nè non junctura porrò debitè moveatur, curandum ut dum Arcus rurſum prorſum vibratur, brachii motum manus aut quaſi dux tantiſper procedat, aut quaſi aſſecla proximè ancilletur.</p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52084:11"/>
                     <p>Ad paradigma proximum in <hi>C fa ut,</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs exprimendum, demittitur chorda infima ad intervallum unius Notae, ut ſic ſiat Octava Chordae antepenultimae, quod in illa Clavi plerumque obſervatur. Vitabis autem fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes quorumdam errores; primò ſi lentè primùm Notas ſingulas, deinde auctâ dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, ac maturâ audaciâ celerius percurras. Secundò, ſi ſategeris ut Arens ac digitorunt motus apprimè conſpirent. Tertiò, ſi Arcus mediocri diſtantiâ tum à Ponticulo, tum ab extremo ſuo cornu ſeu apice Chordas impel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52084:11"/>
                     <head>Quomodo plures ſimul Notae perſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendae ſint.</head>
                     <p>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m plures Notas alias aliis ſuperimpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas conſpexeris, uno omnes ictu ita vil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>andae ſunt, ut ab imâ ad ſupremam, medias in occurſu perſtringendo, progrediatur Arcus; ac ſiniſtrorſum propellatur, ubi ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Notae duplices, triplices, aut plures non niſi ſemel ſe offerunt; aſt ubi ſaepiùs multiplici ſerie continuantur, ad ſiniſtram primò, deinde ad dexteram agitari debet plectrum, Motuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ab imâ ſemper chordâ inchoandus eſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>In Paradigmate figurae <hi>1, 2, 3, 4,</hi> Notis non ſupra verticem ſed ad latus adſcribuntur. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi autem hanc figuram <hi>(1)</hi> in eodem Notarum cumulo ſaepius repetitam videris, indicium eſt primum digitum ad omnes ejuſmodi Notas protendi debere, ut in Thiorbâ ſieri ſolet.</p>
                     <p>Aliud minuritionum Paradigma ſubjungi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Plura, ubi te accurata firmaverit exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatio, ad calcem libri in promptu habes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52084:12"/>
                     <head>De Triplis.</head>
                     <p>TRiplas (ſive Minimis ſive Semiminimis conſtent, ſive eae deinde in tenuiores mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutias dividantur, ſive Baſi communis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurae ſuperſtruantur, adeo ut uni Minimae tres Semiminimae, aut uni Semiminimae tres Chromae, aut uni Chromae tres Semichromae reſpondeant) facilè modulaberis, modo ſingulae menſurae binis utrimque lineis definiantur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Sonorum blanditiis at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Leporibus.</head>
                     <p>LEpôres varii ac elegantiae Notis adhiberi poſſunt, vel Arcu, vel Digitis. Arcu nunc incitatiùs nunc remiſſiùs chordae pulſantur; prout cujuſque genius aut meliſmatis indoles ſuaſerit: quae impulſus varietas eidem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando Notae adhibetur, ita ut exordio ſubmiſſiori paullatim aſſurgat vehementiùs &amp; quaſi intumeſcat. Nonnulli arcu trepidare ac vacillare geſtiunt, cujus frequentior uſus vix probatur. Plures ſubinde conſequentes Notae eodem Arcus impulſu venuſtè exprimuntur.</p>
                     <p>Nec non ſiniſtrae manus digitis varius quaſi color Notis appingitur, vel cum ad vocis aemulationem unius Notae ſonus in ſonum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius quodammodo colliqueſcere cogitur, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito vel retracto digito, paullo poſt Arcus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſum. Id ſi in aſcenſu fiat, <hi>Aſſurrectio;</hi> ſi in deſcenſu, <hi>Delapſus,</hi> vocari poteſt.</p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52084:12"/>
                     <p>Nonnunquam via ſternitur ad Notam, cum in eadem Chordâ, vel à tertiâ inferiori ad eam ſenſim adrepimus, diciturque Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, nunc rariùs in uſu: vel cum idem fit à Tertiâ ſuperiori, eſtque quaſi <hi>Delapſus</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex.</p>
                     <p>Aliquando Nota ſubſequens praecedentis Notae ſonum particulamque mutuatur, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpto ſibi ab alterâ puncti incremento, atque unius ejuſdem vibrationis beneficio utraque Nota coaleſcit; unde <hi>Coalitio</hi> dici poteſt.</p>
                     <p>Accidit etiam, ut exſpirante ferè Notae Sono, alterius digiti appreſſio eliciat acuti neſcio quid, atque adeo Acumen nuncupari queat.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Lepôres ex tremoribus oriundi.</head>
                     <p>DIverſis praeterea tremoribus Notis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcit gratia. Preſſiùs cum tremitur leni admodum criſpatione, vix variatur ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, ſecus, cum apertiùs. Hoc elegantiae genus exoritur, cùm intra Toni diſtantiam fit tremor à loco, à quo aut ad quem tranſit digitus. Hujuſce Tremoris variae ſunt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Cùm ad Notam ſequentem aſſurgit digitus intremiſcens, dicique poteſt <hi>Tremula Aſſurrectio. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Cùm à Nota praecedenti recedit digitus cum Tremore; unde <hi>Tremulus Delapſus</hi> vocari poteſt.</p>
                     <p>Quo pacto vero in Elevatioue, Coalitione, &amp;c. Tremor fiat, ex ipſo Paradigmate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto, ubi ſignis characteriſticis apponuntur Notae exponentes, clariùs eluceſcit.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Lepôres plani.</item>
                        <item>Aſſurrectio.</item>
                        <item>Delapſus.</item>
                        <item>Elevatio.</item>
                        <item>Delapſus duplex.</item>
                        <item>Coalitio.</item>
                        <item>Acumen.</item>
                        <item>Lepôres tremuli.</item>
                        <item>Tremor preſſus.</item>
                        <item>Tremor apertus.</item>
                        <item>Tremula Aſſurrectio.</item>
                        <item>Tremulus Delapſus.</item>
                        <item>Tremula Elevatio.</item>
                        <item>Tremula Coalitio.</item>
                        <item>Criſpata Cadentia.</item>
                        <item>Explicatio;</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52084:13"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Beat. exp: Backfall exp: Double-Backfall exp: elevation. <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>exp Spinger. exp: Cadent. exp: Backfall Shaked exp: <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Close Shake. exp: Shaked Beat. exp: elevation exp: <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Cadent. exp: Double. Relish exp: or thus: exp: </p>
                     <p>For theſe, I am obliged to the ever famous Charles Colman Doctor in Muſick</p>
                     <p>Si quid praeterea in vocis ornamentis, Trillis, Gruppis, reliquiſque Teretiſmis ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare eſt, digitorum blandimento ſimplicique Arcus vibratione ad Chelyn concinnè tranferri poteſt.</p>
                     <p>Inter has elegantias aliae ſunt Maſculinae, ut Aſſurrectio &amp; Delapſùs, Baſſoque potiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm conveniunt: aliae Femininae, quae ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet Tremore leni vel nullo fiunt; Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique ſeu Netodo inſerviunt maximè: ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metſi pro varietate affectuum, Amoris, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris, Audaciae, Timoris, ubilibet compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere queant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52084:13"/>
                  <head>PARS SECUNDA.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Melotheſiae Compendium.</head>
                     <p>MElotheſiam ſeu Compoſitionem Muſicam aliquot hîc praeceptis complecti viſum eſt. Quâ in re, tametſi quidam à Tenore ſeu Meſodo, nempe quòd illi Parti in Cantu Eccleſiae plano ſeu Gregoriano ceterae accinant atque ſubſerviant, reliquorum concentuum rationem diſtantiamque deſumant; in noſtrâ tamen Methodo, à Baſſo ſeu Hypatodo quaſi à Subſtrato ac Fundamento caeterarum Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Intervalla numerare multò erit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuniùs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Intervallis.</head>
                     <p>PRimùm contemplationi ſe noſtrae ſiſtit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſonus ſeu Iſophonos, ejuſdem vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet Soni ſeu Notae Repelilio, vel potiùs duarum Notarum in eundem Sonum conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio; valetque perinde ac <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas in Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticâ, Punctum aut Centrum in Geometriâ, eſtque in nulla diviſibilis intervalla. Dum Soni ab <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſono plùs minùſve recedunt, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria oriuntur Intervallorum genera. Secunda inprimis, quae dividitur in perfectam &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectam: Perfecta vocatur Tonus, qui in duos ex aequo Semiſſes, ſi Soni proportionem ſpectes, findi nequit. Attribuuntur ei à pleriſque novem Commata ſeu minora ſeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta; quorum bina conſiciant Diaſchiſma, quatuor Semitonium Minus, quinque Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonium Majus, adeo ut diſcrimen inter utram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que hanc Secundam imperfectam ſit unius Commatis, quam differentiam Apotomen nuncupant. Nonnulli ſubtiliùs obſervant aliquid Tono deeſſe, quo minus novem Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata expleat; itidem Semitonio Majori quo minùs quinque, Minori quo minùs quatuor attingat. Sed haec cùm ad noſtrum inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum haud admodum conducant, aliis quibus vacat, penſiculatiùs indaganda relinquimus, uti &amp; caeterorum Intervallorum accuratiores minutias.</p>
                     <p>Tertia dividitur in perfectam ſeu majorem quae Ditonus vocatur, &amp; imperfectam ſeu minorem quae dicitur Semeditonus. Notan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum verò particulam <hi>Semi</hi> ſeu <hi>Seme</hi> hic
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52084:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>atque alibi ſaepe, non ſigniſicare Semiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem ſed defectum Soni, utpote qui ad juſti intervalli metam non pertingat.</p>
                     <p>Quarta dividitur in majorem quae Trito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dicitur, eſtque intervallum prohibitum, &amp; minorem quae Diateſſaron nuncupatur.</p>
                     <p>Quinta dividitur in Perfectam, quae Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente appellatur; &amp; Imperſectam, quae Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiapente, ſeu falſa Quinta, vocatur.</p>
                     <p>Sexta dividitur in majorem, quae Hexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chordon majus, ſeu Tonus cum Diapente di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, &amp; minorem quae Hexachordon minus ſive Semitonium cum Diapente nominatur.</p>
                     <p>Septima dividitur in majorem, quae Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonus cum Diapente, &amp; minorem quae Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miditonus cum Diapente nuncupatur.</p>
                     <p>Octava dividitur in Perfectam, quae Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſon (ſeu per omnes chordas) appellatur, &amp; Imperfectam quae Semidiapaſon dicitur.</p>
                     <p>His Intervallis variae Concordantiae ac Diſcordantiae continentur, quarum geneſis ac ordo ſubjecto Schemate exhibetur, in quo Octavam vides in duodecim diviſam Hemito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, cujuſmodi in Chelyos Canone aliiſque Inſtrumentis ſecundùm Scalam Diatonicam reperire eſt; ubi quia plura quam duodecim Segmenta ſeu diaſtemata non diſtinguuntur, nullum diſcrimen (quoad Intervalla) apparet inter Tritonum &amp; Semediapente; cùm utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque diſtantia à quintâ perfectâ unius dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat ſit Semitonii: quamvis in praxi Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonus Quartae, Semediapente Quintae ſpeciem prae ſe ferat.</p>
                     <figure/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52084:14"/>
                     <head>De Concordantiis.</head>
                     <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atuor ex his vocantur Concordantiae; Iertia, Quinta, Sexta, Diapaſon, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque Octavae; Tria reliqua intervalla di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur Diſcordantiae; Secunda, Quarta (tametſi hanc quidam Concordantiis ſubinde annumerent) Septima, earumque Octavae.</p>
                     <p>Inter Concordantias duae ſunt Perfectae; Quinta &amp; Octava: ita dictae, quòd aures plenâ quadam Voluptate permulceant. Reliquae duae ſunt Imperfectae, Tertia &amp; Sexta; ita nuncupatae, quòd tenuiori concentu aure's recreant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Tranſitio Concordantiarum.</head>
                     <p>OBſervandum porrò duas Perſectas ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem generis Concordantias ſibi invicem ſuccedentes, verbi gratia, duas ſimul Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, aut binas continenter Octavas, quòd au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum nimiâ ſatietate oppleant, prohiberi; niſi forte adverſis ſibi motibus, (in pluribus preſertim partibus) occurrant, aut in eadem ſede conſiſtant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Illicita Illicita Licita Licita Licita in pluribus partibus</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 5 5 5 8 8 8 8 5 5 5 8 8 8 8 8 5 5 5 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Not allowed Not allowed Allowed Allowed Allowed in many parts</p>
                     <p>A Quintâ tamen ad Octavam, aut ab Octavâ ad Quintam promiſcuè tranſiri poteſt; modò altera Pars ſixa in ſtatione permaneat, aut non niſi gradatim ſe moveat. Nam ſi Partes per ſaltum unà progrediantur, minus grata iſta Perfectarum collocatio accidet.</p>
                     <p>Imperfectae vero Concordantiae aſcendendo aut deſcendendo continuari poſſunt.</p>
                     <p>Denique ab unâ Concordantiâ ad aliam tranſire nil vetat, modo evitetur Relatio non harmonica, quae tum accidit, cùm Nota mollis durae inconcinnè abſouéque opponitur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52084:15"/>
                     <head>De Melotheſiae Clavi ſeu Tono.</head>
                     <p>OMnis porro Melotheſia ad Clavem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſeu Tonum reducitur, in quo nimirum Baſſus poſt varias fluctuationes quaſi in Portu anchoram jacit. Tonus durus dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, cùm Tertia ſupra Notam Toni cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem dura eſt ſeu Ditonus. Tonus denominatur Mollis, ſi praedicta Tertia mollis fuerit ſeu Semiditonus.</p>
                     <p>Mollis Durus Mollis Durus Mollis Durus<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mollis Durus Mollis Durus Mollis Durus<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mollis Durus Mollis Durus<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Obſervandum porrò Tonos Duros, tametſi alii aliis peregriniores appareant, omnes eſſe non affines modò ſed ejuſdem planè indolis; adeò ut per Tranſpoſitionem, non ſolum quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot hîc ſunt reliqui, ſed quotquot omninò excogitari poſſunt, ad primum in <hi>G.</hi> nullo negotio revocentur. Quod de Tonis Mollibus perinde intelligendum eſt.</p>
                     <p>Ad Tonum Baſſi partes caeterae componum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                     <p>Horum omnium periculum optimè fiet in Contrapuncto. Eſt autem Contrapunctus cùm Nota ſupra Notam, ſine coloribus, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicè conſtruitur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52084:15"/>
                     <head>Quâ ratione Baſſus conformandus ſit.</head>
                     <p>IAciatur itaque imprimis fundamentum; hoc eſt, Baſſus concinnetur iis legibus: Primò, ut Tono conveniat, Cadentiis interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis, ſiquae fuerint, aſſumptis finali clauſulae haud alienis; in Quintâ videlicet aut Tertiâ ſuperiùs. In Tonc tamen duro vice Tertiae, in quâ Cadentia minimè convenit, aſſumatur Quarta aut Secunda.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 3 5 4 2</p>
                     <p>Secundò, Baſſus moveatur plerumque per Saltus ad Tertiam, Quartam, &amp; Quintam; gradibuſque duntaxat iis gaudeat, quibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Toni fines coerceatur. Cantus autem gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dario ut plurimùm inceſſu procedat.</p>
                     <p>Tertiò denique, auſpicium ſumatur à Tono molli, ſepoſitis conſultò, ad majorem facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, Notis duris.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quo pacto Cantus Baſſo adſtruendus ſit.</head>
                     <p>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>perſtrue porro Cantum Baſſo, adhibendo Tertias, Quintas, Octavas (ſecluſis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſper Sextis, quae Notis duris congruunt max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè) ut quaeque vicinior magiſque in promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu eſt. Numeroſque arithmeticos <hi>3, 5, 8,</hi> ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pote Concordantiarum characteres inſcribe; ut ſic vel ad oculum pateat cujuſmodi ſint.</p>
                     <p>Cantus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Baſſus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Notandum verò, ubi partes pauciores con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinunt, imperfect as Concordantias praelegen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das perfectis, ut aurium faſtidio conſulatur. Hinc in Biciniis rarò uſurpatur Octava, niſi in principio, clauſulâ finali, aut intermediâ, velcùm partes contrariis incedunt motibus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52084:16"/>
                     <head>De Triphoniis.</head>
                     <p>HIſce peractis, ſi alteram fortè Partem annectere velis, verbi gratiâ, Altum, cujus ſedes eſt proximè infra Cantum, vide Concordantiis utaris, quae ad Cantum propius accedunt; Tertiamque in alterutrâ Parte nunquam omittas, dum Tricinium adornas.</p>
                     <p>Cantus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Altus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Baſſus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Vides in Paradigmate Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; Altum ambos in Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vâ deſinere; quod in Tono molli convenientius videtur, quàm ſi Cantus tranſiſſet in Tertiam duram, quae in ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ Clauſulâ gregariae atque interiori Parti in Polyphoniis potiùs convenit.</p>
                     <p>Quando Baſſus aſſurgit ad Quartam, aut deſcendit ad Quintam, Nota quae praecedit hujuſmodi aſcenſum vel deſcenſum requirit Tertiam majorem; unde ſecundam &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultimam Alti notam duplicato decuſſi ad gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Ditoni elevatam vides.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Tetraphoniis.</head>
                     <p>UBi te in Triphoniis jam ſatis exercue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ad Tetraphonia tranſire poteris, caeteris Partibus adjuncto Tenore. Quaedam autem hic obſervanda. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Pars aſſumpta adornetur Concordantiis, quantum fieri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit, ab utraque aliâ Parte diverſis. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quam proximè Alto ſubnectatur; tum enim harmonia perfectiſſima conſurgit, cùm Partes ſuperiores maximè ſunt affines atque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminae. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t duarum Quintarum &amp; Octavarum conſecutionem non minùs inter ſuperiores Partes, quam inter illas &amp; Baſſum aſcendendo aut deſcendendo fugias.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52084:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>In Paradigmat, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultimam Alti, in duas Semiminimas diviſam vides, quarum prior Notae praecedenti colliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, unde ligatura voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Cadentiamque ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornat plurimùm: quod imitari poteris qualibet in Parte, quae Ditonum Baſſo occinit in Notâ pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultimâ.</p>
                     <p>Cantus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3 5 3 5 3 5 5 3 5 8</hi> Altus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>8 3 8 3 8 3 3 8 3 8</hi> Tenor.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5 8 5 8 5 8 8 5 8 3</hi> Baſſus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi huic Methodo aſſueveris, majori deinde cum libertate omnes ſimul Partes componere fas erit, quavis cuilibet parti attributâ Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordantiâ, modò ſua ſingulis aſſignetur, nec interea omittatur Tertia.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Sexta.</head>
                     <p>HActenus nihil actum de Sexta; quae tum adhibetur (loco Quintae) cùm Baſſus in Notis duris verſatur, quales ferè ſunt Ditonus ſupra Tonum Melotheſiae, Semiditonus infra, atque illa Nota quae Primariae proximè ſubſtat; ejuſmodi enim notae durae Sextam poſtulant. Vide Paradigma.</p>
                     <p>Cantus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3 6 3 3 3 3 8 3 5 8</hi> Altus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>8 3 3 8 8 6 5 8 3 8</hi> Tenor.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5 8 6 5 5 3 3 5 8 3</hi> Baſſus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>1 2 3</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Notandum vero <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Quintam &amp; Sextam in Contrapuncto nunquam ſimul uſurpari. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Semitonium infra Cardinalem Baſſi Notam Octavam ſine aurium offenſione non admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere; quare amandatâ Octavâ duae partes in eadem potius Tertiâ invicem complecti de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Baſes quae notis ut plurimùm conſtant poſcentibus Sextam, paucioribus quàm pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52084:17"/>Partibus aptiores eſſe. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Baſſum, cùm ejuſmodi Notas recipit, carere ad ſui complementum ac latitudinem debitam, Ditono inferiori; quem ſi ſubnectas, jam Sextae mutabuntur in Octavas, Tertiae in Quintas, quaeque fuiſſet Semitonii Octava ſed inconcinna, jam cum lepore fit Tertia.</p>
                     <p>Cantus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3 8 5 3 3 5 8 3 5 3</hi> Altus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>8 5 3 8 8 8 5 8 3 8</hi> Tenor.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5 3 8 5 5 3 3 5 8 5</hi> Baſſus.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ex his omnibus patet, non niſi tres reperiri Conſonantias eodem ſimul tempore Baſſo inſiſtentes; eae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſunt Tertia, Quinta, vel Sexta, &amp; Octava. Quòd ſi plures quàm quatuor Partes compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere animus eſt, praedictae conſonantiae in ſuis Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitis ſen Octavis reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentandae ſunt; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde, dùm duarum Quinta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aut Octavarum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutionem declinas, ſuavem ac verſicolorem Melodiae texturam conſurgere neceſſe eſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quis Diſcordantiis locus ſit.</head>
                     <p>DIſcordantiarum in Muſicâ duplex eſt uſus. Primò, in Diminutione; cùm videlicet binae, trinae, aut plures Notae ſibi invicem gradatim ſubnexae, uni alterius Partis Notae reſpondent. Providendum tamen, ut primitia Nota ſit Concors.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5 4 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 6 7 8 7 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 8 7 6 5 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 3 4 5 6</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3 4 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 5 4 5 6</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hic obſerva duas, tres, aut plures ſubinde Notas in eadem lineâ vel Spatio conſiſtentes, inſtar unius longioris notae conſiderari poſſe; atque adeo eaſdem omnino pati Diſcordantias, quas admitteret Nota illa integra longior, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus hae particulae cenſentur.</p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52084:17"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>7 6 5 4 3 2 3 8 7 5</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>8 2 3 4 5 6</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secundò, Diſcordantiis locus eſt in Syncopſi ac Ligaturis; cùm nimirum pars una nexu quodam ac colligatione duarum Notarum in eâdem ſtatione detinetur, atque ab alliſione alterius Partis quae interea progre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur quaſi conſcindi videtur: habetque id plurimum elegantiae, ſi non temerè ſed cum iudicio fiat.</p>
                     <p>Syncopſis in Dyphoniis.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>8 7 6 6 5 4 3 4 6 7 6 8 3 4 3 4 3 4 3 23 8 3 23 2323 2 3 4 6 4 3 8</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5676 7676 76765 4 38 3 4 3 4323 8 8 7 6 5 3656 7 6 5 4 3 8</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Syncopſis in Triphoniis.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5 6 7 6 85 6 7 65 7 6 8 3 65 3 65 3 65 4 3 8 5656 5656 7 6 5 8</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>323 3 3 3 4 3 3 3 3 3 843 843 843 8 3 3 3 3 434 3 4 3 8</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Et quamvis Diſcordantia initio alicujus Notae in Baſſo applicatur, nihil intereſt, modò particula prior ligaturae ei Concors ſit, ac deinde Diſcordantiam emolliat Concordantia ſubſequens, quae Imperfecta plerumque eſſe debet.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52084:18"/>
                     <p>Auribus verò per diſcordantias concordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaſque imperfect as variâ expectatione tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis atque ſuſpenſis tum demum fiet ſatis, cùm in perfectis Concordantiis Melodia quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo colliqueſcit. Idcirco enim Diſcordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis in Muſicâ conceſſus eſt locus, tùm, ut va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietati conſulatur, tùm, ut ejuſmodi aſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate quaſi vellicatae aures Conſonantiarum ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſione levari ac permulceri geſtiant.</p>
                     <p>Tranſitus autem Diſcordantiarum ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordantias imperfectas maximè vicinas fieri ut plurimum debet: quod etiam in progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione Imperfect arum ad perfectas obſervandum eſt. Hinc Sexta major ad Octavam, minor ad Quintam genuino lapſu pergit. Atque hac aequabili gradatione, ſuavior abſque incon ditâ ſubſultatione Melodia redditur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Tritono, &amp; Semidiapente.</head>
                     <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>amvis ſupra dictum ſit, Tritonum &amp; Semidiapente intervalla prohibita, ac Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordantias plerumque cenſeri; eſt tamen eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum uſus nonnunquam in Muſica elegantiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Nam etiam abſque Syncope Baſſo cum gratiâ opponuntur, quod aliis diſcordantiis, niſi forte veterani Muſurgi peritiâ ſcitè attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perentur, vix conceditur.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Semidiapente Tritone Tritonus. Semidiapente.</p>
                     <p>Curandumque ut Tritonus ad Sextam, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiapente ad Tertiam tranſeat.</p>
                     <p>Example.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Tritonus. Semidiapente.</p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52084:18"/>
                     <p>Diximus praeterea Quintam vnà cum Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ in eadem Contrapuncti plani ſede comparêre neutiquam poſſe: Secus eſt, quando Semidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente in poſteriori parte ligaturae adhibetur; tunc enim requirit Patrocinium atque unbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum Sextae, ut ſeſe auribus gratiùs ſiſtat. Quo in caſu, ſi rectè expendatur, Semidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente ſupplet locum diſcordis Septimae, ac Sexta ei imminens obit vices Octavae; ut facile patebit, ſi Baſſum ad Tertiam inferiùs demiſeris.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Contemplatio Concordantiarum Muſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</head>
                     <p>ATque hîc quis non jure merito obſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcat, cùm animum ſubit ex Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantiis dumtaxat tribus, paucis ſubinde intertextis diſcordantiis, tam innumerabilis prognata ſoboles, ut quicquid unquam Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſiae fuit vel futurum eſt, ex his quaſi elementis coaleſcat. Auget admirationem per ſeptem diſtributa Gradus, (unde haec concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia diſcors emanat) tam apta Sonorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexio, eodem literarum ordine in Scalâ Muſicâ exhibita, quo recurſantes per annum dierum Hebdomadas primaevae rerum originis imaginem repraeſentamus.</p>
                     <p>Numerum hunc <hi>Orpheus</hi> faſtis immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus conſecravit, cùm Lyram ſuam, (quae à <hi>Pythagora Samio</hi> in <hi>Aegyptiorum</hi> adytis reperta olim, atque è tenebris in bono lumine collocata, <hi>Alexandri</hi> temporibus etiamnum ſuperſtes fuit) Heptachordam eſſe voluit; ut ſeptenis Fidibus ſeptem Planetarum diſcurſus atque concentum, quoties fila pulſaret, auribus atque animo ſiſteret. Neque verò abſimilis eſt Sonorum ac Siderum harmonia, cùm illorum concordia horum aſpectibus ad amuſſim reſpondeat. Iſophonia ſiquidem Aſtrorunt refert Conjunctionem; exiremi Diapaſon termini, Oppoſitioneni; comprehenſae intra Octavam Concordantiae, Tertia, Quinta, Sexta, Trinum, Sextilem caeteroſque in Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaco aſpectus intermedios. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tque Planeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum varia inter ſe collocatio orbi inferiori alios atque alios impertit influxus, ita diverſa Sonorum Eucraſia miros in auribus animiſque motus excitat, quibus in omnis harmoniae authorem admirabili ſurſum contemplatione rapiantur. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ſuum in Templis ſacriſque locum Muſica jure meritò vendicat.</p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:52084:19"/>
                     <p>Nec vacat Myſterio, ternos per intervalla ſonos invicem ſuperimpoſitos univerſae Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniae medullam ac ſummam ambientis vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi nodo nexuque complecti. Divinae illius Monadis Triadiſque, nutu ſuo omnia in ordine pondere et mènſurâ gubernantis, non leve ſimulachrum; quo nihil ad Muſicae landem illuſtrius, nihil excellentius.</p>
                     <p>Reliqua itaque huc attexere, tametſi admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa, nil attinet; cujuſmodi ſunt, fidem pulſatam ab alterâ homophonâ ſide etiam intactâ reſponſionem quodammodo aliquam acclamationemque accipere: Tubas, caeteraque ejuſmodi oblonga inſtrumenta pneumatica, Sonos gradatim conſequentes modulanti ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare, niſi prius per ſolitas concordantias Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titando exordium feceris.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Muſicarum Concordantiarum Analogia ad Planetarum aſpectus.</head>
                     <p>SEptem in ſequenti Schemate gradatim ſoni, quos intra Limites Diapaſon, ſtilus Diatonicus exhibet, in lineâ Diametro arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticè repraeſentantur. Circulus Zodiacum refert, aſpectumque Planetarum, cujus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectionibus Octavae partitiones exactè reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Extremi ſiquidem ejus termini Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem Oppoſitionemque imitantur. Partitio media, quae hinc Quartam, inde Quintam reſpicit, <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> adumbrat. Tertia ac Sexta Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vam ut <g ref="char:trine">△</g> ac * Hemicyclum explent. Quibus adde, Octavam duodecim conſtare Hemito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis; non ſecus ac Zodiacus ſigna duodecim variis animalium figuris deſcripta comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitur.</p>
                     <p>Figura infima Omnes omnino ſonos quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot concentum ſimul efficiunt, Ternarii Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniâ identidem repetitâ contineri demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52084:19"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Benedicta sit ſancta et individua Frinitac</head>
                     </figure>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52084:20"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52084:20"/>
                  <head>CHELYS, Minuritionum Artificio Exornata. PARS TERTIA.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quâ ratione Minuritiones ad Baſin ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandae ſint.</head>
                     <p>MInuritio ad Baſin nihil aliud eſt, quàm aut ipſius Baſeos, aut aliarum Partium, quae Baſi accini poſſunt, in varias melicas Minutias Sectio; unde vulgò Diviſio Muſica appellatur. Ea, uti omnium ferè Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Muſicorum, ita Chelyos imprimis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio Summa eſt. Rem omnem, ſi cui peregrina eſt, verbo primùm complectar; deinde fuſius artis documenta ſubjungam.</p>
                     <p>Fundamentum quodvis rectè concinnatum bis deſcribitur; cujus exemplar alterum Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gano, Clavicymbalo, ſeu alii Inſtrumento ſuſtinendum traditur; alterum ob oculos Muſurgi variis Melodiae elegantiis exornan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum proponitur, quibus inventionem dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatemque pariter oſtentet: quod nonnullis faeliciter adeo ſuccedit, ut Auditores non modo ſingulari voluptate permulceant, ſed admiratione etiam incredibili non rarò per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellant.</p>
                     <p>Quòd ſi ad tantam excellentiam primaſque pertingere paucis conceditur, ac reliquis certè in ſecundis non ſine laude conſiſtere licebit; ſi, quod inventioni deeſt, dexteritate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plere, atque aliorum compoſitiones concinnè modulari nitatur: tametſi enim hoe admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis minus fortaſſe habeat, quòd hîc alienâ utendum ſit operâ, ac ſedula praemeditatio plerumque antecedat, Melotheſiae tamen prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiâ exactéque modulandi induſtriâ plus ſaepe affert voluptatis. Atque ut ab hoc infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riori gradu ad altiorem conſcendere pluribus in promptu ſit, viſum eſt hujuſce artificii fontes omnibus aperire, ac publici juris fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52084:21"/>
                     <head>Minuritionum genera.</head>
                     <p>EX Definitione jam traditâ, triplex ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcitur Minuritionum ſpecies.</p>
                     <p>Prima ſimpliciſſima, quae Fundamentalis dici poteſt, utpote quae fundamenti duntaxat longiores Notas, in breviores celerioreſque dividat.</p>
                     <p>Secunda magis compoſita, quae Melotheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca nominari poterit; nempe, quae Baſſo ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Partium minutias ſuperſtruit.</p>
                     <p>Tertia ex utraque mixta, quae fractiones tum Baſſi, tum aliarum Vocum, vel agglome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratis conjunctim, vel ſparſis ſigillatim Notis exhibet.</p>
                     <p>Hae pro cujuſque genio promiſcuè, nullo ſervato ordine, uſurpari poſſunt. Nos vero ut ordinem doctrinae obſervemus, à ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioribus ad complexa ſeu compoſita progre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diemur.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Minuritio Fundamentalis.</head>
                     <p>MInuritio Fundamenti variè perficitur, dùm <hi>Semibrevis</hi> in duas <hi>Minimas,</hi> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor <hi>Semiminimas,</hi> octo <hi>Fuſas,</hi> ſexdecim <hi>Semifuſas,</hi> &amp;c. comminuitur.</p>
                     <p>Idque fit primò cum Minutiae vel in eadem <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſonâ ſede, vel in Octavâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secundò, cum variatur quidem Sonus, deflexione tamen adeò exiguâ, ut tenuis admodum Melodiae immutatio percipiatur; dum à Notâ diminutâ tantillum receditur, ac ſubito ad eam regreſſus fit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52084:21"/>
                     <p>Tertio, cum Minutiae adhibentur per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Tranſitionis de Notâ ad Notam, uti in appoſito Paradigmate videre eſt, ubi tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ad ſingula unius Octavae intervalla, tum in aſcenſu tum in deſcenſu repraeſentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3 4 5 6 7 8</hi> Aſcending. <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcending <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>2 3 4 5 6 7 8</hi> Aſcending. <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcending <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>2 3 4 5 6</hi> Aſcending. <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcending. <hi>7 8 2 3 4</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>5 6 7 8</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ascending <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Descending</p>
                     <p>Adjecimus praeterea exemplum in Claviſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periori, cùm hic tranſitionum decurſus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus paſſim vocibus inſerviat.</p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52084:22"/>
                     <p>Quartò, quando Minutiae à Notâ dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutâ in alias Concordantias per Saltus proſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liunt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>853 468 85635 853468 853</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Quinto, dum ad dictas Concordantias gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datim pergitur, trium aut quatuor Notarum ſeſe conſequentium fluxu continuo. Qui modus etſi ferè ad Secundam Minuritionum Speciem pertineat, cùm tamen Baſin potiſſimùm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciat, cujus Notis, perexiguâ exorbitatione, inhaerit, ad primam revocari non immeritò poteſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Theſe paſs up to the 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Theſe to the 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to a 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> higher Theſe to a 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> higher. <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Theſe to a 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Theſe to a 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to an 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to a 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> higher <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>2 Theſe paſs to the 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Theſe to a 6.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Theſe to the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Theſe into Concords both above and below.</p>
                     <p>Curandum verò <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> ut minutiae, dum ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordantias tranſeunt, ad Baſin harmonicè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruantur. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ad proximam Baſis Notam affini quodam Motu ſuaviter perlabantur. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Si quando minutiae ad Diſcordantiam tranſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, id locis congruis, ubi eae videlicet in Melotheſia adhiberi aſſolent, et ex arte fiat.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>As thus. Exemp: Gratiâ. <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>3</hi> This puſses into a 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> This into a 7.<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52084:22"/>
                     <p>Minuritio ad initium ſequentis Notae aptè deducetur, ſi (ut ferè contingit in tranſitione ad Concordantias) tres aut certè duae ultimae minutiae ad hujuſmodi Notam gradatim aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant vel deſcendant: ut in adjecto. Paradig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate demonſtratur, ubi Semibrevis in G. dividitur per varias tranſitiones ad quodlibet intervallum Diapaſon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>As thus or thus Thus or thus Thus or thus <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Thus or thus &amp;c: <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Atque hic incedendi modus probatur, ſive lentior ſive velocior ſit minuritio, quae quo ſuerit incitatior, plures minutias poſtulabit, uti experientia conſtat.</p>
                     <p>Jam verò quemadmodum harum regularum intelligentiam praxis perficiet, ita praxin ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus facilitaſque conſequentur. Hanc in rem juvabit Fundamentum aliquod facile ſeu ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum concinnare, cujus Notas ſingulas ad praecedentium praeceptorum normam in varias Minutias frangas.</p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52084:23"/>
                     <p>Cavendum autem <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> ut nativo quodam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſu, quod ſuprà monuimus, Minutiae fluant: nec Notae durae aut molles temerè inſerantur, niſi quas Melodia Fundamenti ac Toni indoles exigit.</p>
                     <p>Notandum <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>,</hi> Septimam ac Sextam in deſcenſu aequipollere Secundae aut Tertiae in aſcenſu, ut exemplo hic demonſtratur.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 8<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>7 6 5 4 3 2 8</p>
                     <p>Atque adeò eodem redit, ſive ſuccedenti Notae in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſono occurras, ſive in Octavâ. De Octavis enim eadem eſt ratio.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Baſis, vel ad Quintam deſcendendo vel ad Quartam aſcendendo, Cadentiam prae ſe fert, Notas quae vel in Tertia ſuperiùs vel inferiùs in Sexta ei accommodantur, duras plerumque eſſe oportet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimò quemadmodum Minuritio Baſin ſupergreditur in Tertiâ aut Quintâ; ita ad earumdem Concordantiarum Octavas, hoc eſt, ad Sextam, &amp; Quartam, cum inferius mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur, delabi debet.</p>
                     <p>535 535 535<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>464 464 464</p>
                     <p>Hiſee praecognitis, Baſin in Minutias fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere proximo Paradigmate diſces: ubi clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis cauſâ minutiae Singulis Fundamenti Notis ſuperſcribuntur.</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52084:23"/>
                     <p>An Example of Breaking the Ground<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52084:24"/>
                     <p>In ſecundâ autem variatione, ſub initium tertiae menſurae, Baſi occurritur in Tertiâ; qui videlicet occurſus eo loco maximè vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur genuinus; adeoque iſthic atque alibi ad imitationem proponitur; ſi quando Melodiae decurſus iſtiuſmodi contextum ſuaſerit. Non abſimilem occurſum in Quintâ, tertia menſura variationis tertiae exhibet.</p>
                     <p>Diſputant nonnulli, quid in Minutiis de Septimâ Superiùs &amp; Secunda inferiùs ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum ſit; debeatne videlicet duritiem indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere, tametſi natura mollis ſit. In iſtiuſmodi ſubitis mutationibus, tametſi aurium potiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè judicio ſtandum ſit, plerumque tamen haec regula obſervari poteſt, ut dùm à Notâ cardinali ad Secundam aut Septimam deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, rurſumque ad eandem Notam aſcendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſignum <hi>B</hi> duri [*] apponatur.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Niſi fortè Baſis cadat vel aſſurgat ad Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam Mollem, aut tranſeat ad Tertiam, aut denique per modum Cadentiae progredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur ad Quartam ſuperiùs, aut Quintam inferiùs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Suadetur ut ſub Cadentiam finalem Nota penultima ad Quartam ſuperiùs aut Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam inferius ſimpliciter tranſeat; ne dùm per Minutias ad clauſulam gradatim deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, Minuritio Fundamenti, duas conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter Octavas alicui Parti ſuperiori, quae ab Organoedo exprimitur, temerè impingat; idque tum in Diminutionibus, tum in Choro maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè, Polyphoniiſque cavendum eſt, ubi iſta Octavarum Conſecutio magis apparet.</p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52084:24"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Not allowed. Not allowed. Allowed. Allowed.<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 8 88 88<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Illicita. Illicita. Licita. Licita.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Minuritio Melothetica.</head>
                     <p>DIffert Melothetica à Minuritione ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici Fundamentali, quòd illa Notas Baſis duntaxat concerpit, nunc ſuprà nunc infrà (haud longâ tamen ambage) ab iſto ſuo Polo digrediens: Haec verò Baſſo uſque ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminet, ac coelo liberiore fruitur, è quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet voce ſeu Parte ſuperiori Minutias verſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colores depromens, Concordantiis debitis vel ſaltuatim vel gradatim Baſſum inumbrans, Diſcordantiaſque legitimè intertexens.</p>
                     <p>Regulas eaſdem admittit quas Melotheſia; perque Tertias, Quintas, Octavas incedit: Quintarum aut Octavarum conſecutionem evitans; Tropoſque affectat conſimiles iis, quos in Minuritione ſimplici deſcripſimus. <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Minutias in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſono perſiſtentes. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Soni variationem, ſervato in diminutionibus eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ferè Melodiae tenore. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Tranſitiones de Notâ ad Notam, aſcendendo vel deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo per duos aut tres vicinores gradus. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Concordantiarum ex aliâ in aliam deſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torios motus. <hi>5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> Liberiorem per plures gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ad varias Concordantias decurſum.</p>
                     <p>Diſcordantiae, ut dictum eſt, ſub initium menſurae, niſi in Syncope, non adhibentur. Sexta diminutionem rarò inchoat, niſi forte in ligaturâ, aut ubi eam Baſis deſiderat vice Quintae; cùm ſcilicet duriores Baſſi Notae Sextam minorem expotunt, aut Molliores etiam majorem, ad melodiae ſuaviorem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textum depoſcunt, uti in Paradigmate liquet.</p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:52084:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>6 66 6 6 6</p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi vides Baſſo deeſſe ad ſui complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Tertiam inferiùs, quae hic nigricante Notâ adumbrata eſt, qua rurſus demptâ, Minuritio quae Octavam effecerat, jam ad Sextam redit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>6 6 6</p>
                     <p>At ſi Quinta loco Sextae adhiberetur, ea ad Baſin, ſi ad Tertiam inferius demittteretur, Diſcors foret.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Minuritio Mixta</head>
                     <p>SImplicem atque Compoſitum unà com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectitur, ad quam ſpectat quilibet dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aut plurium Partium concentus, Chely eodem ſimul tempore auribus repraeſentatus, ſive id fiat disjunctis ictibus, ſive eadem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratione conjunctis. Quod diminutionis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, uti caeteris praeſtat, ita plus requirit in Melotheſiâ peritiae atque judicii, ob frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores Syncopas, quibus Diſcordantiae haud rariùs quam in aliâ quavis Muſicâ, hujuſmodi Melodiae interſeruntur.</p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:52084:25"/>
                     <p>Exempli gratiâ Paradigmata ſequentia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibemus. Cumque in Cadentiis difficultas maxima momentumque ſit, in iis potiſſimum hujus artificii ſpeciem edimus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Cadentiarum duo genera.</head>
                     <p>CAdentiae verò tametſi videantur innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merae, ad duplex genus revocantur. Primùm cùm à Septimâ per Sextam tranſitur ad Octavam, Baſſo delabente ad Secundam inferiùs. Secundum, cùm à Quartâ per Tertiam ad Octavam fit gradus, Baſſo ad Quintam inferiùs aut Quartam ſuperiùs ſe promovente.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>76 76 43 43</p>
                     <p>Paradigma ſequens primi generis Caden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ejuſque Minuritiones ſimplices, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitas, mixtaſque, tum disjunctim, tum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctim, ob oculos ponit.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Minuritio</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ground Broken.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Fundamentalis.</item>
                        <item>Simplex.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Deſcant.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Melothetica.</item>
                        <item>Compoſita.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mixt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mixta.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:52084:26"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Example upon the first ſort of Cadence <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <p>In praecedenti Paradigmate obſervare eſt, ad plures Fundamenti Notas unicam in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuritione compoſitâ continuari, quod ſaepe aut ad pathos aut ad varietatem fit. Habes hîc praeterea tranſitum à Septimâ per Sextam ad Octavam, atque ubi Baſis Sextas poſtulat, id figurâ <hi>[6]</hi> deſignatur. Animadvertendum denique, partem finalis Notae ſubinde dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui, quod cujuſque arbitrio relinquitur.</p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:52084:26"/>
                     <p>Paradigma ſequens, Notis duris Caden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam exhibet, ut, quamvis idem ferè hîc minuendi modus, qui ſupra, obſervetur, quanta nihilominus Melodiae diſcrepantia mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es duraſve conſequatur Notas, auribus aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Example upon the first ſort of Cadence Sharp <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:52084:27"/>
                     <p>Paradigma proximum, ſecundi generis Cadentiam exhibet in Minimis.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Example of the Second Sort of Cadence upon a Minim <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ground Broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <p>Quòd ſi ſingulas praecedentis Paradigmatis Notas alterum tantum producas, ſpecimen dabunt Cadentiae in Semibrevibus. Id tamen ſeorſim Paradigmate ſequenti oſtenditur; ubi nonnullas Notas praevias appoſuimus, ut eâdem operâ plures gradatim Notas diminuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di modum habeas.</p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52084:27"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Example of the Second Sort of Cadence upon a Semibreve <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Descant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:52084:28"/>
                     <head>De Quintis &amp; Octavis in Minuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</head>
                     <p>AT, ne in praecedenti exemplo Octavarum alicubi conſecutio quempiam offendat, conſiderandum eſt, num diverſa a Baſſo Pars, ut in minuritione melothetica fit, prae manibus ſit, an Baſis ipſa, ut ſit in fundamentali, ubi Octavarum conſecutio haud ſecus admitti po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ac in Organo, Clavicymbalo, Teſtudine, quae, ſingularum ferè Notarum Octavas ad pleniorem harmoniam aſſumunt.</p>
                     <p>Quintarum Conſecutio omnino exploditur, niſi earum altera ſit Quinta falſa; tum enim non modo nihil vitii ſed multum habet leporis atque elegantiae; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ſepoſito Antiquorum faſtidio à Recentioribus admittitur.</p>
                     <p>Paradigma ſequens in Brevibus Cadentiam proponet, quatuor antepoſitis Minimis grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim aſcendentibus.</p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:52084:28"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>An Example of the Second Sort of Cadence upon a Breve <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Descant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52084:29"/>
                     <head>De Sextis &amp; Tertiis in Minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritione.</head>
                     <p>IN Minuritione Mixtâ horum Paradigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, plures ſimul Sextae itidemque Tertiae occurrunt: in quibus haec tenenda regula. Cùm eodem ictu impelluntur Chordae, Tertiae gratiores facilioreſque accidunt: Cùm diverſis atque per ſaltus incitantur, Sextae ut pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum adhibendae: Saltus enim quò remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſunt, eo Majori varietate aures recreant. Quapropter in Minuritione ſubſultante, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimas potiùs quam Tertias alternatim uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</p>
                     <p>Ad Cadentias proximè accedit Clauſula quaedam ei admodum affinis, in graviori Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicâ ſatis uſitata, cùm Baſſus deſcendit ad Quartam aut aſſurgit ad Quintam, Notae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que finalis prior pars in Melotheſiâ frangitur hoc modo.</p>
                     <p>Hujuſce generis Paradigma in Minuritionibus exhibemus, praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis quatuor Semibrevibus, ut diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicultatem quae Tyronibus in Notis longioribus amplificandis obverſari ſolet, nonnihil levemus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Notae ſurſum deorſumque caudatae, duarum Chordarum in uniſono percuſſionem indigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52084:29"/>
                     <p>An Example of a Cloſe without a Cadence</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52084:30"/>
                     <p>Praecedens Paradigma tripaex Minuritio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num genus non admittit, ob Fundamenti moram in eodem ſede diuturniorem, ut conſideranti patebit. In eo tamen ſatis elucet Methodus diminuendi Notas etiam longiores.</p>
                     <p>Hactenus Minuritionum tria genera ſeor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim collocavimus, quae tamen in eadem Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phâ inter ſe commiſceri nil vetat. Imò ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem etiam Notae heterogen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Minuritio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenti Paradigmate contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ur: ubi vides priorem Notae partem Minuritione ſimplici ſeu fundamentali, poſteriotem Minuritione Melotheticâ exornatam.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Semiminimis.</head>
                     <p>Quae hucuſque de Minimarum, Semibre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium, aliarumque Notarum longiorum fractionibus dicta ſunt, celerioribus facile applicare eſt; cùm eadem ferè ſit utrobique ratio. Ne quid tamen hîc deſiderent Tyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, idem in Notis brevioribus, Semiminimis &amp; Fuſis, adumbrabimus. Ac primùm de Semiminimis gradatim vel aſcendentibus vel deſcendentibus.</p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52084:30"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>An Example upon Crochets aſcending by Degrees <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Descant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:52084:31"/>
                     <p>Paradigma Semiminimarum gradatim deſcendentium.</p>
                     <p>An Example upon Crochets deſcending by Degrees</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Descant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <p>Nunc verò idipſum in Semiminimis per ſaltum diſpoſitis demonſtrandum.</p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52084:31"/>
                     <p>An Example of Crochets riſing and falling by Leaps</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Descant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52084:32"/>
                     <p>In ſuperiori Baſi omnia unius Octavae In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervalla percurruntur. In primâ Strophâ Tertiae deſcendentes aequipollent Sextis aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus; Quartae aſcendentes, Quintis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendentibus. In Secundâ Strophâ è con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo, Tertiae aſcendentes aequiparantur Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis deſcendentibus; Quartae deſcendentes, Quintis aſcendentibus. Septimae in ſuis oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis Octavis, hoc eſt, in Secundis includuntur, ubi ſurſum vel deorſum fit ſine ſaltu gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De Fuſis.</head>
                     <p>SI fortè Fuſae occurrent in Baſi, cui ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicandae Minuritiones, diſpiciendum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primìs eſt, num Fuſae accipiendae ſint ut ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantivae fundamenti partes, an verò ut ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jiciales Minutiae alicujus longioris Notae, ornamenti aut tranſitionis causâ adhibitae; ut in ſubſequenti gradatione apparet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hic vides Minutias illas aequivalere lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioribus Notis, quae illis in Paradigmate proximè adſcribuntur: Quare Minuritiones ad praedictas longiores Notas, perinde ac ſi Fuſae iſtae non interveniſſent, motu contrario accommodari nil vetat, in exercitatione prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim extemporali.</p>
                     <p>Quod ſi Fuſae Subſtantivae ac Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales ſint, inque Minuritiones frangendae, habes hic appoſita Paradigmata, quorum id imitatione perficias. Ibi primùm quid in gradatione tum deſcendendo tum aſcendendo agendum ſit, oſtenditur; deinde quid in diſcretis per ſaltum Intervallis.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:52084:32"/>
                     <p>An Example upon Quavers Riſing and Falling by Degrees</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The ground The Ground broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground Deſcant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground Mixt <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt</p>
                     <p>Hic praeter morem regulaſque jam traditas alternae Notae non in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſono aut Octavâ ſed in Secundâ Baſin excipiunt: id tamen quaedam illic neceſſitas Notarumque velocitas excuſat. At ſi pari ratione Semiminimae in Fuſas, Minimae in Semiminimas comminuerentur; id aegrè admodum paterentur aures ob diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turniorem in ſecundâ moram. Attamen ſi gradarius ille aſcenſus aut deſcenſus Notas punctis alternatim interſtinct as haberet, jam Minuritio nativo curſu ordinatim proflueret, quemadmodum in Exemplo vides.</p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:52084:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Ground Broken Ground Broken</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>De <hi>b</hi> Molli &amp; Duro.</head>
                     <p>HIc ſi quaeras, cur Fuſae in <hi>B,</hi> appoſitum ſit <hi>b</hi> molle; id propterea ſit, quòd Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuritio inde ad <hi>F</hi> mollioris itidem ſoni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendat; uti paulò poſt, <hi>F.b.</hi> duro atollitur; quia nimirum inde ad <hi>B.</hi> ſimiliter durum aſcenditur: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>triuſque porro ratio eadem reddi poteſt, ut <hi>Relatio non harmonica</hi> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur auribus planè ingrata, quae tùm perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tratur, cùm quatuor Notae gradatim aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, aut deſcendentes, terminos perfectae Quartae excedunt. Nam licet Quarta minor paſſim in uſu ſit, attamen ſi Nota altera ab alterâ remotiùs divaricetur, enaſcitur Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonus harmoniae infeſtus; quod ne ſiat, à priore ad poſteriorem ſternenda et emollienda eſt via: atque hîc tria Quartarum genera obſervari poſſunt: Tritonus, Diateſſaron, &amp; Quarta minor, cum nimirùm ſuperior Nota mollis, inferior dura eſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>De Fuſis per ſaltus incedentibus id dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum reſtat, videri iſtiuſmodi conſtructionem ad Baſin Minuritionum minus idoneam. Si tamen occurrant, eadem regula hîc inſervire poterit, quae de Semiminimis tradita eſt, converſis Semiminimis in Fuſas, Fuſis in Semifuſas &amp;c. Quid praeterea in iis ſit agendum, ſequens Paradigma planum facit.</p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52084:33"/>
                     <p>Quavers moving by Leaps</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The ſiround broken <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Deſcant <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Mixt Mixt</p>
                     <p>His praemiſſis de extemporali ad Baſin Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitatione agendum.</p>
                     <p>Primùm ſeligatur Baſis Semibrevibus aut Minimis, aut utriſque conſtans; ejuſmodi enim ad extemporaneam Exercitationem aptiſſima.</p>
                     <p>Deinde ad manum habenda quaedam Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuritionum Schemata ſeu Figurae, quae pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Fundamenti Notis accommodata, ſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus itidem ſimili filo applicari poſſint.</p>
                     <p>Hac Supellectile inſtructus auſpicare luſum à Schemate omnium facillimo, atque enitere ut à primis illud Notis ad extremam uſque Baſin deducas, pari texturâ. Id cum fueris aſſecutus, aliud atque aliud Schema, ſimili conatu aggredere.</p>
                     <p>Hujus tibi Exercitationis Figuras aliquot unà cum idoneâ Baſi, ſequens Paradigma exhibet: quibus innumeras alias tuo ipſe marte attexes.</p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52084:34"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>The Ground points <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Horum Schematum ampliſicationem a tque ad reliquam Baſin applicationem è proximo exemplo colliges.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52084:34"/>
                     <p>An Example for carrying on a point upon a Ground</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52084:35"/>
                     <p>Ejuſmodi amplificatio cujuſcumque Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis, Inventioni non leve affert ſubſidium, eamque omni anxietate liberat, dum nihil admodum elaborandum venit, niſi ut prima Schematis ratio ad totam Baſin conſimili Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxi applicetur. Hinc praeterea oritur Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuritionum analoga compoſitio, jucunda ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum, modò ne eâdem ſigura nimiâ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcatione faſtidium creet, cui facile mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur interpoſita ſubinde, ut in praecedenti Paradigmate vides, verſicolor tranſitio, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſorumque Schematum alius ex alio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Minuritionum Syntaxis.</head>
                     <p>PRincipio Fundamentum ipſum ſimplici ac liquidâ modulatione percurre: idque <hi>1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Minuritionum Subſtratum ab Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus clariùs atque diſtinctiùs percipiatur. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Baſin tu ipſe ejuſque genium melius comprehendas. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t, qui tibi fundamentum accinit, probè intelligat, quo Menſurae tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peramento uti velis.</p>
                     <p>Deinde Baſin in varias Minutias Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minimarum atque Fuſarum diſpeſce, aut ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot fioſculos Melotheticos lentioris menſurae adſperge; idemque in Secundâ &amp; tertiâ Strophâ, ſi forte totidem Baſis contineat, fieri poterit.</p>
                     <p>Tum verò Minuritiones celeriores earum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> varia Schemata atque amplificationes, ut ſupra oſtendimus, adhibe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi hoc genere luſus dexteritatem audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus probaveris, ad Melothetica ornamenta ſubtiliora Syncopaſque tranſire licebit, nunc intenſiori, nunc remiſſiori manu, ut ſtudio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiùs abblandiaris auribus, attentionemque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilies.</p>
                     <p>Demùm varios Minuritionum ſaltus atque tripudia, cum multiplici Triplarum genere, in medium produces; laxando Inventionis habenas, animoque, quà vocat liberiùs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgendo; varietati inprimis atque aptae figurarum collocationi ſtudens, quò novâ identidem attentione Auditorem allectes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que multiplices aſſectionum motus, Muſicae imperio rapias.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52084:35"/>
                     <head>De Baſi Continua,</head>
                     <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>od ſi Baſis non per Strophas, ſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peluo curſu ad exitum procedat (ut cùm pro fundamento Baſſus Continuus alicujus Motecti aut Madrigalis aſſumitur) prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio ſedato ac merâ Baſi inchoandum erit, ut Organoedus menſurae quâ velis uti, teno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem aſſequatur. Poſt aliquot verò Semibreves, ad Minuritiones quas animus ſuggeſſerit, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi poteris; donec ad clauſulam pervene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, quae Manui exerendae campum aperiat. Pauſis aliquot ſubinde interpoſitis, concede Organoedo nonnihil ſpatii quo te praecedat, ut illum deinde lepidâ aemulatione conſequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Varias demum Melotheſias, Minuritio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Mixti generis, Triplas ac caetera Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis Myrothecia eſſunde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Minuritiones ſingulari Chely quâ ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione aptandae.</head>
                     <p>PRaeter ea quae jam diximus, id curan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum maximè in concinnandis Minuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus, ut Symmetriae facilitatique conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las. Nam ex duabus Melotheſiis aeque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantibus, ea meretur Palmam, quae faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liori negotio ac leviori manu percurri poteſt: ſatiſque liquet, eum qui Canonis indolem digitorumque applicationem neſciat, vix eſſe ad Minuritionum compoſitionem idoneum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſicem.</p>
                     <p>Adhibenda porrò ſunt ad exemplum, alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opera, quorum induſtria in excogitandis Minuritionibus cum laude deſudavit. Quos inter, D. <hi>Henrici Butler,</hi> &amp; D. <hi>Danielis Norcome</hi> elucubrationes, aliorumque No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratium, quibus pulſandae Chelyos praeroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva facilè conceditur, praecellentium Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, nunquam ſine acroamate uſurpari poterunt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Quâ Methodo duae Cheles Baſi alludere debent.</head>
                     <p>HAec hactenus de Chely Simplici; nunc agendum de duplici. Cùm duobus ſimul Muſurgis ad eandem Baſin componendae atque accinendae erunt Minuritiones, hae ſerventur regulae.</p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:52084:36"/>
                     <p>Primò Fundamentum in triplici chartâ deſcribatur, quarum prima Organoedo qui literâ <hi>A.</hi> deſignari poterit, ſecunda ei qui primam pulſat Chelyn literaque <hi>B.</hi> notabitur, tertia illi qui ſecundâ canit Chely, inſignie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turque <hi>C.</hi> ſeorſim tradendae ſunt.</p>
                     <p>Exordiantur <hi>A.</hi> &amp; <hi>B.</hi> Baſinque ſimplici modulatione percurrant, interea dum <hi>C.</hi> graviorem aliquam Melotheſiam Baſi appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Dumque <hi>B.</hi> eandem cum aliquâ varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Melotheſiam redintegrat, <hi>C.</hi> ſoli Baſi immoretur. Atque eadem methodus ſive duae ſint Fundamenti Strophae ſive unica, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur; altero Baſin, altero Melotheſiam modulante.</p>
                     <p>Secundò, <hi>C.</hi> in procurſum Minuritionum celeriorem exſiliat, cum <hi>B.</hi> ſimile quid, ſublimiori tamen ſtylo reponat. Id ut feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciùs eveniat, auſpicetur Luſum is qui In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventione pollet, ſequatur qui manu expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori praecellit, ut aſſurgat potius quam flac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſcat Muſica.</p>
                     <p>Tertiò, poſt iteratam Chelyum altercatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, <hi>A.</hi> ſi dextrâ valet, ſigno dato, ſuam quoque Minuritionum Symbolam in medium proferat; atque interea Chelys altera Baſin, altera Melotheſiam graviorem moduletur. Tum denique Chelys utraque ſeorſim, Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noedi Minuritiones haud impari artificio aemuletur.</p>
                     <p>Quarto, partiri inter ſe poterunt Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pham aliquam Fundamenti propoſiti; ita ut <hi>B.</hi> ſimpliciter Baſin frangat, nec niſi ad Octavam ſurſum aut deorſum excurrat, ſive in eadem Notâ conſiſtat, ſive ad ſequentem tranſitum paret. Quod cum Muſurgo <hi>C.</hi> conſiiterit, eandem orbitam facilè evitabit, ſeque ad Tertias, aut Quintas, aut ſicubi id Baſis requiret, ad Sextas, ſubducet, Baſique in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſono aut Octavâ ad Notam finalem dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat occurret; atque adeò Quintarum &amp; Octavarum obſtrepera colliſio etiam in extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porali praxi haud aegrè declinabitur.</p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:52084:36"/>
                     <p>Quintò, <hi>C.</hi> Minuritionem aliquam incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abit, quae ſpatium Brevis aut Semibrevis occupet, iaque, ſigno dato, Muſurgo <hi>B.</hi> indicabitur, qui eodem temporis ſpatio Socii Schema in ſequentibus Notis imitabitur; idque ad Strophae exitum alternis deduci poterit. Similis concertatio ad breviora vel longiora, intervalla, varietatis ergò, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatur.</p>
                     <p>Sextò, Signum dari poterit Organoedo, ſi callet artem, ut Schema aliquod ipſe quoque hac poſtremâ methodo auſpicetur, quod poſt Brevem, Semibrevem, aut ſimile Spatium, utraque Chelys aut ſeparatim aut conjunctim excipiat; ſervatâ hac regulâ, ut dum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctim canitur, altera Notas lentiores adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, dum altera in Minuritionibus circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volitat.</p>
                     <p>Septimò, Chelys utraque, Organoedo ad Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin ablegato, priorem concertationem celeriùs aut lentiùs renovare poterit, ac denique per varias Triplarum aliarumque proportionum formas, liberiùs evagari, vel perpetuis vel intercalatis Strophis: donec tandem junctis ambae viribus, aut quaſi tumultuario con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſu, aut ſi id potius libuerit, temperatâ ſuavique clauſulâ coronidem labori imponant.</p>
                     <p>Atquae haec extemporaria concertandi ratio inter aſſuetos invicem ſodales, adeò feliciter aliquando vertit, ut plauſum etiam majorem quam ſtudioſius adornatae Minuritiones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portarit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Minuritiones plurium Partium Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi ratio.</head>
                     <p>IN componendis Minuritionibus pro duobus Baſſis, regula praecedens quid agendum ſit ſatis demonſtrat: nimirum jam huic jam iſti Parti attributo Choragi ſeu Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis officio, ſuperiorem aut inferiorem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciam
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52084:37"/>alternis obtinebunt; ac denique poſt appoſitas aemulaſque concertationes, in unum ambo foedus atque amplexum vel junctis Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuritionibus vel ſuavi Melotheſiae texturâ conſpirabunt.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Minuritiones pro duabus ſuperioribus Partibus, methodo Melotheticâ concinnandae ſunt; dumque ſimul ambae incitatiùs ferun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, in Tertiis aut Sextis plerumque invicem reſpondere gaudent, aliis ſubinde Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantiis interjectis, habitâ nimirum ſemper Fundamenti ratione. Caetera, nihil à ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioribus regulis diverſum occurrit.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>3.</hi> Si Baſſo atque Superiori Minuritiones adaptandae ſunt, perpendenda eſt utriuſque Partis indoles; quâ probè perſpectâ Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticas fractiones Superiori, Fundamentales Diminutiones Baſſo ut plurimùm tribues.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>4.</hi> Eâdem ſolertiâ Minuritionibus pro duobus Baſſis &amp; Superiore, item pro duobus Superioribus &amp; Baſſo utendum eſt.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi>5.</hi> In Minuritionibus pro tribus Baſſis, Superioris, Mediae aut Inſimae Partis Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutiones euilibet per vices tribuendae ſunt. Verum Minuritiones pro tribus Partibus ad certam Baſin vix ſolent aptari; ſed liberiore, per modum Fantaſiae, ut vocant, decurſu ſine certâ lege hinc inde divagantur: Exordio plerumquè ſeveriore, adeoque per modum Fugae incedant, Minuritionum alternâ ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatione in medium conjectâ, conglobatâ ſubinde concertantium acie; demum quaſi pactis induciis, ſuavi ac placido plenioris concentus Epiſodio, dextras Muſicamque jungant.</p>
                     <p>Subtexi poſſunt ad levandum faſtidium Meliſmata varia, Allemandae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:52084:37"/>
                     <p>Hujus generis Minuritiones variis Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus accommodas, nos haud ſanè paucas in Apollineae Academiae Tyronumque gratiam claboravimus. Plures reperire eſt inter exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia D. <hi>Joannis Jenkins</hi> Opera: de cujus aliorumque noſtratium Authorum immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in Muſicam Rempublicam monumentis ac meritis, cùm ſupra invidiam ſint, meâque laudatione creſcere nequeant, praeſtat ſilere quam fruſtra dicere.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52084:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The DIVISION-VIOL,</hi> OR The Art of Playing <hi>ex tempore</hi> to a GROUND.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>Of the <hi>VIOL</hi> it ſelf, with Inſtructions how to Play upon it.</head>
                     <p>A VIOL in the hands of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Violiſt may (no doubt) be reckon'd amongſt the beſt of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Inſtruments. To Play <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> to a Ground is the higheſt perfection of it: And this is the Subject of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſe. But firſt we muſt treat of ſome things neceſſary to that deſigne; as namely, Firſt, a Viol fitted for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; Next, Hands enabled to Play upon it; And then, ſome knowledge in the Concords of Muſick. With theſe therefore we will begin, in aſſiſtance to ſuch as are not ſufficiently informed therein: And firſt concerning the <hi>VIOL.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 2.</hi> What kind of Viol is fitteſt for Diviſion, and how to be accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</head>
                     <p>A Viol for Diviſion, ſhould be of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a leſſer ſize than a Conſort Baſs; that ſo the Hand may better command it: more or leſs ſhort, according to the reach of his fingers, who is to uſe it: but the ordinary ſize, ſuch as may carry a String of thirty Inches from the Bridge (duely placed) to the Nut. The Sound ſhould be quick and ſprightly, like a Violin; and Viols of that ſhape (the Bellyes being digged out of the Plank) do commonly render ſuch a Sound.</p>
                     <p>It muſt be accommodated with ſix Strings; and with ſeven Frets, like thoſe of a Lute, but ſomething thicker. If alſo you faſten a ſmall Fret, at the diſtance of an Octave from the open Strings (which is the middle betwixt the Nut and the Bridge) it will be a good Guide to your Hand, when you ſtop that part of the Finger-board.</p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52084:8"/>
                     <p>The Strings a little bigger than thoſe of a Lyra-Viol; which muſt be laid at the like nearneſs to the Finger-board, for eaſe and convenience of Stopping.</p>
                     <p>The Bridge, as round as that of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort Baſs; that ſo each ſeveral String may be hit with a bolder touch of the Bow.</p>
                     <p>The Plate, or Finger-board, exactly ſmooth and even. Its length, full two parts of three, from the Nut to the Bridge. It muſt alſo be of a proportionate roundneſs to the Bridge; ſo, that each String may lye at an equal nearneſs to it. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: If the Roundneſs of the Bridge, be as the Arch <hi>A. B.</hi> then I would have the low end of the Finger-board to be as <hi>C. D.</hi> and the top of it, as <hi>E. F.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>Viol-makers may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice hereof.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 3.</hi> What kind of Bow.</head>
                     <p>A Viol-Bow for Diviſion, ſhould be ſtiff, but not heavy. Its length (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two places where the Hairs are faſtened at each end) about ſeven and twenty Inches. The Nut, ſhort. The height of it about a fingers breadth, or little more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 4.</hi> How to hold or place the Viol.</head>
                     <p>BEing conveniently ſeated, place your Viol decently betwixt your knees; ſo, that the lower end of it may reſt upon the calves of your legs. Set the Soles of your feet flat on the floor, your Toes turn'd a little outward. Let the top of your Viol be erected towards your left ſhoulder; ſo, as it may reſt in that poſture, though you touch it not with your hand.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 5.</hi> How to hold and move the Bow.</head>
                     <p>HOld the Bow betwixt the ends of your Thumb and two foremoſt fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, near to the Nut. The Thumb and firſt finger faſtned on the Stalk; and the ſecond fingers end turned <hi>in</hi> ſhorter, againſt the Hairs thereof; by which you may poize and keep up the point of the Bow. If the ſecond finger have not ſtrength enough, you may joyn the third finger in aſſiſtance to it; but in Playing Swift Diviviſion, two fingers and the Thumb is beſt.</p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52084:8"/>
                     <p>Holding the Bow in this poſture, ſtretch out your arm, and draw it firſt over one String and then another; croſſing them in right angle, at the diſtance of two or three Inches from the Bridge. Make each ſeveral String yeild a full and clear ſound; and order your knees ſo, that they be no impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the motion of your Bow.</p>
                     <figure/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52084:9"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 6.</hi> The poſture of the Left Hand.</head>
                     <p>WHen you are to ſet your fingers upon the Strings, you muſt not graſp the Neck of your Viol, like a Violin; but rather (as thoſe that Play on the Lute) keep your Thumb on the back of the Neck, oppoſite to your fore-finger; ſo as your Hand may have liberty to remove up and down, as occaſion ſhall require.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 7.</hi> How the Viol is Tuned, and applyed to the Scale of Muſick.</head>
                     <p>WE now ſuppoſe you to underſtand Song, and conſequently the Scale of Muſick; which known, the Tuning of your Viol appears in ſuch order as you ſee the ſix Semibreves which ſtand one over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the firſt part of the following Scale: where note, that all the degrees ariſing above the higheſt of thoſe Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breves, are expreſs'd on the Treble or higheſt String, by ſtopping it ſtill lower and lower towards the Bridge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Your Viol being tuned according to the ſix Semibreves, your next buſineſs is, to play thoſe other Notes, which you ſee aſcend and deſcend by degrees, over which I have ſet Figures to direct you with what Fingers to ſtop them; 1, 2, 3, 4, is ſet for firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth Finger. Thoſe which have no figures over them, are played on the open Strings.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 8.</hi> How the ſame Notes may be play'd upon different Strings.</head>
                     <p>YOU muſt know that ſometimes Notes are play'd, not on thoſe Strings to which they ſeem properly to belong; but for eaſe or better order of Fingering, are play'd upon ſome other String: An Inſtance whereof you have in thoſe two Notes marked with little Stars over their Figures; which Notes, are play'd upon the ſecond String; though, a little before, Notes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52084:9"/>ſtanding in the ſame places were played upon the Treble or firſt String: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when any difficulty ſhall occur in Fingering, you are to conſider how the ſame Notes may be expreſs'd with moſt eaſe and convenience to the Hand.</p>
                     <p>The Example before-going was ſet in the whole Scale; that you might better perceive where every Line and Space take their places upon the Viol: But thoſe that follow, muſt be ſet down in the uſual way of five Lines; and when Notes exceed that Compaſs they are reduced again into the ſaid five Lines by ſetting another Cliff.</p>
                     <p>This which follows I would have you practiſe, firſt in a ſlow meaſure; increaſing the quickneſs by degrees, as your Hand ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth in readineſs: and be ſure to make all your Notes ſound clear and full; preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Strings firm and hard with the very ends of your Fingers. Alſo give as much Bow to every Quaver, as the length thereof will permit. But before you ſet upon it, read the two Rules which follow it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 9.</hi> A Rule for Holding on the Fingers.</head>
                     <p>WHen you ſet any Finger down, hold it on there; and play the following Notes with other Fingers, until ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion require the taking it off. This is done as well for better order of Fingering, that the Fingers may paſs ſmoothly from Note to Note, without lifting them too far from the Strings, as alſo to continue the Sound of a Note when the Bow hath left it. Inſtances of theſe Holds (for ſo they are called) you have, where you ſee ſuch a Stroke as this <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:direct"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>direct</ex>
                        </expan> drawn from One to ſome other diſtant Note unto which you muſt hold it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52084:10"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 10.</hi> A Rule for the Motion of the Bow.</head>
                     <p>WHen you ſee an even Number of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or Semiquavers, as 2, 4, 6, 8. You muſt begin with your Bow forward; yea, though the Bow were imployed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the next Note before them. But if the Number be odd, as 3, 5, 7; (which alwayes happens by reaſon of ſome Prick-Note or odd Reſt,) the firſt of that odd number muſt be played with the Bow back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. This is the moſt proper motion of the Bow, though not abſolutely without ſome exception: for ſometimes the quickneſs of the Notes may force the contrary, as you will ſee in the end of the fifth Example. Alſo quick Notes skipping from the Treble to the Baſs, and ſo perſued, are beſt expreſs'd with contrary Bows. Let your next practice be this which followes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 11.</hi> Of ordering the fingers in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Notes.</head>
                     <p>IN any point of Diviſion which reaches to the lower Frets or beyond them; the higheſt Note thereof is alwayes ſtopt either with the third, or with the fourth finger: If with the third, the firſt and ſecond fingers take their orderly places in ſtopping the two Notes gradually aſcending to it, or deſcending from it. If the higheſt Note imploy the fourth finger, then the next Note under it is ſtopt either with the third or with the ſecond finger, according to the ſaid under Note being flat or ſharp: If ſharp, with the third; If flat, with the ſecond finger. But whether the higheſt Note imploy the third or fourth finger, the <hi>Third</hi> below doth alwayes imploy the firſt finger, which ſerves as a Guide to thoſe two Notes above it. And whereas you will ſee ſometimes two ſucceſſive Notes ſtopt one after the other with the ſame finger, it is alwayes done either to prepare the fingers to this poſture, or to remove the ſaid poſture to ſome other place. This Order of Fingering holds good throughout the whole Finger-board (in ſtopping three
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52084:10"/>gradual Notes upon one String) with this difference only, that where the Stops are wide (as amongſt the Frets) the fourth or little finger is of more requiſite uſe than it is lower down where the Stops are more contract.</p>
                     <p>As for the poſture of the Fingers in moving from one String to another, I muſt refer you to your own obſervation, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of what Finger doth offer it ſelf the apteſt for ſtopping any ſucceeding Note.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>If you find difficulty in this Example, play it the ſlower, until your Hand have overcome it.</p>
                     <p>I muſt now propoſe unto you Notes of a quicker Motion, <hi>viz. Demiſemiquavers;</hi> but not before I have ſaid ſomething of</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 12.</hi> The Motion of the Right Arm and Wriſt.</head>
                     <p>I Told you before that you muſt ſtretch out your Arm ſtreight, in which poſture (playing long Notes) you will neceſſarily move your ſhoulder Joint; but if you ſtir that Joint in quick Notes, it will cauſe the whole body to ſhake; which (by all means) muſt be avoyded; as alſo any other indecent Geſture. Quick Notes therefore muſt be expreſs'd by moving ſome Joint nearer the Hand; which is generally agreed upon to be the Wriſt. The queſtion then ariſing is about the menage of the Elbow-Joint; concerning which there are two different opinions. Some will have it kept ſtiff; Inſomuch, that I have heard a judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Violiſt poſitively affirm, that if a Scholar can but attain to the playing of Quavers with his Wriſt, keeping his Arm ſtreight and ſtiff in the Elbow-Joint, he hath got the maſtery of the Bow-Hand. Others contend that the motion of the Wriſt muſt be ſtrengthened and aſſiſted by a compliance or yielding of the Elbow-Joint
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52084:11"/>unto it; and they, to back their Argument, produce for inſtance a perſon famous for the excellency of his Bow-hand, uſing a free and looſe Arm. To deliver my own opinion; I do much approve the ſtreightneſs of the Arm, eſpecially in Beginners, becauſe it is a means to keep the Body upright, which is a commendable poſture. I can alſo admit the Stiffneſs of the Elbow, in Smooth and Swift Diviſion; for which it is moſt properly apt; But Croſs and Skipping Diviſion cannot (I think) be ſo well expreſs'd without ſome conſent or yeilding of the Elbow-Joint unto the motion of the Wriſt. To gain this Motion of the Wriſt, the ordinary direction is, to draw the Hand (in moving the Bow to and fro) a little after the Arm. Or you may try how you can play the firſt Example of <hi>Quavers</hi> by moving your Wriſt only, keeping your Arm ſtreight in the Elbow-Joint; a little practice will effect it. This Motion or looſneſs of the Wriſt we mention, is chiefly in <hi>Demiſemiquavers;</hi> for, in <hi>Quavers,</hi> and <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quavers</hi> too, we muſt allow ſo much ſtiffneſs to the Wriſt as may command the Bow <hi>on,</hi> and <hi>off</hi> the String, at every Note, if occaſion ſo require.</p>
                     <p>I will ſet your next Example in <hi>C fa ut,</hi> with the loweſt String put down a Note, as we commonly do when we play in that Key. And, as I have formerly admoniſh'd you to practiſe your Examples firſt flow and then faſter by degrees, that admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is moſt requiſite in Swift Diviſion, where alſo you muſt be carefull that the Motion of your Bow and Fingers do equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwer each other, bearing your Bow moderately ſtiff upon the Strings, at a convenient diſtance from the point thereof; by which means you ſhall make your ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Notes more diſtinguiſhable: A thing in which many fail, either through want of a due complyance of the Bow to the Strings, or not exactly croſſing them at a right diſtance from the Bridge, or elſe by playing too near the point of the Bow; which errors I note, that you may avoyd them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>The little peece at the end of this Example, is ſet as an exception to what was ſaid (<hi>pag.</hi> 5.) of Beginning each eaven number with a Forward Bow; for here you muſt play them (as neceſſity will enforce you by reaſon of their quickneſs) ſome forward, and ſome backward.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52084:11"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 13.</hi> How to order the Bow in dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Stops.</head>
                     <p>WHen two, three, or more Notes ſtand one over another (as you have in two places of the laſt Example) they muſt be play'd as One, by ſliding the Bow over thoſe Strings which expreſs the ſound of the ſaid Notes. When <hi>one</hi> of them comes by it ſelf, it is commonly play'd with a forward Bow; but if divers of them fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſucceſſively (as in the paſſages hereto annexed) then each other muſt of neceſſity by play'd by drawing the Bow back; but whether back or forward, be ſure to hit the loweſt String firſt (inſiſting thereon ſo long as need requires) and let the Bow ſlide from It to the higheſt, touching in its paſſage thoſe in the middle betwixt them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>The figures for more convenience, are here ſet before the Notes. Where you ſee this figure (1) ſet before two or three Notes in the ſame Stop; it ſignifies that the firſt finger muſt be laid over all the ſaid Notes: in which, and in all double Stops, the poſture of the left hand is the ſame as if you play'd upon a <hi>Thiorba.</hi> One Example more, and we have done.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52084:12"/>
                     <p>When you have practis'd theſe Examples according to the Inſtructions given, you may then, for variety, look upon ſome of thoſe Diviſions at the end of this Book; amongſt which ſome are eaſie, made purpoſely for Learners; Others require the hands of a good Proficient. And becauſe in thoſe (as alſo in other mens Diviſons) you will meet ſometimes with <hi>Tripla's</hi> of divers ſorts, I will ſpeak ſomething of them in this place.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 14.</hi> Of Tripla's.</head>
                     <p>SOmetimes the Grounds themſelves are <hi>Tripla-time,</hi> conſiſting (uſually) of three <hi>Semibreves,</hi> or three <hi>Minims,</hi> or three <hi>Crotchets</hi> to a Meaſure. Sometimes you may meet with a <hi>Tripla</hi> upon a <hi>Tripla;</hi> as for inſtance, when upon a Ground con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of three <hi>Minims</hi> to a Meaſure, each <hi>Minim</hi> is divided into three <hi>Crotchets,</hi> ſix <hi>Quavers,</hi> or the like. Again, in Diviſions upon <hi>Grounds</hi> of the <hi>Common-Time,</hi> you will meet now and then with divers <hi>Tripla's,</hi> as ſometimes three <hi>Crotchets</hi> to a <hi>Minim,</hi> producing ſix <hi>Quavers,</hi> twelve <hi>Semiquavers,</hi> &amp;c. Sometimes three <hi>Quavers</hi> to a <hi>Crotchet,</hi> and ſometimes three <hi>Semiquavers</hi> to a <hi>Quaver;</hi> the Meaſure of all which, will not be hard to find out, where the quantity of each <hi>Semibreve</hi> is marked out with Strokes or Bars.</p>
                     <p>It now remains, that in directing the Hand I ſpeak ſomething concerning the Gracing of Notes: and though it depend much upon Humour and Imitation, yet I will try how far it may be deliver'd in words and Examples.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 15.</hi> Concerning the Gracing of Notes.</head>
                     <p>GRacing of Notes is performed two wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> by the Bow, and by the Fingers. By the Bow, as when we play Loud or Soft, according to our fancy, or the humour of the Muſick. Again, this Loud or Soft is ſometime expreſs'd in one and the ſame Note, as when we make it Soft at the <hi>beginning,</hi> and then (as it were) ſwell or grow louder towards the <hi>middle</hi> or <hi>ending.</hi> Some alſo affect a Shake or Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the Bow, like the Shaking-Stop of an Organ, but the frequent uſe thereof is not (in my opinion) much commendable. To theſe may be added that of Playing two, three, four, or more Notes with one motion of the Bow, which would not have that Grace or Ornament if they were play'd ſeverally.</p>
                     <p>Graces performed with the Fingers are of two ſorts, <hi>viz. Smooth</hi> and <hi>Shaked.</hi> Smooth is, when in riſing or falling a Tone or Semitone, we draw (as it were) the Sound from one Note to another, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Voyce; and is expreſſed by ſetting down or taking off the Finger a little after the touch of the Bow. In aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it makes that Grace which we call a <hi>Plain-Beat,</hi> or <hi>Riſe;</hi> in deſcending, that called a <hi>Back-fall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52084:12"/>
                     <p>Sometimes a Note is Graced by ſliding up to it from a Third below, called an <hi>Elevation,</hi> now ſomething obſolete. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the Third above, which we call a <hi>Double Back-fall.</hi> This Sliding a Third, is performed commonly upon one String.</p>
                     <p>Again, a Note is ſometimes Graced by joyning part of its Sound to the Note fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, like a <hi>Prick-crotchet</hi> whoſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Quaver</hi> is placed with the enſuing <hi>Note,</hi> but play'd with the ſame Bow of his <hi>Prick-crochet;</hi> This we have called a <hi>Cadent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is yet another Plain or Smooth Grace called an <hi>Acute</hi> or <hi>Springer,</hi> which concludes the Sound of a Note more acute, by clapping down another Finger juſt at the expiring of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 16.</hi> Shaked Graces.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SHaked Graces</hi> we call thoſe that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by a Shake or Tremble of a Finger, of which there are two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> Cloſe and Open: <hi>Cloſe-ſhake</hi> is that when we ſhake the Finger as cloſe and near the ſounding Note as poſſible may be, touching the String with the Shaking finger ſo ſoftly and nicely that it make no variation of Tone. This may be uſed where no other Grace is concerned. <hi>Open-ſhake,</hi> is when a finger is ſhaked in that diſtance from whence it was removed, or where it is to be ſet down; ſuppoſing the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance exceed not the wideneſs of two Frets, for wider than that we never ſhake. Graces made with <hi>Open-ſhakes</hi> are theſe; a <hi>Beat,</hi> a <hi>Back-fall,</hi> an <hi>Elevation,</hi> a <hi>Cadent,</hi> and a <hi>Double Relliſh.</hi> The <hi>Beat</hi> is the ſame in nature with the <hi>plain Beat,</hi> the difference only a ſhort ſhake of the finger before we fix it on the place deſigned. This, as alſo the <hi>plain Beat,</hi> is commonly made from the Half Note, or diſtance of one Fret. The <hi>ſhaked Back-fall</hi> is alſo the ſame in nature with the <hi>plain,</hi> the difference only a ſhake of the finger taken off, which muſt be done in the ſame wideneſs as it ſtood. How an <hi>Elevation, Cadent, Double Relliſh,</hi> &amp;c. imploy the <hi>Open-ſhake,</hi> will better appear in their Examples which follow; in which <hi>(exp.)</hi> ſtands for <hi>Explication.</hi> The Notes which have an Arch or Stroke over or under them, are play'd with one motion of the Bow.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Smooth Graces.</item>
                        <item>A Beat.</item>
                        <item>Back-fall.</item>
                        <item>Elevation.</item>
                        <item>Double Back-fall.</item>
                        <item>Cadent.</item>
                        <item>Springer.</item>
                        <item>Shaked Graces.</item>
                        <item>Cloſe-ſhake.</item>
                        <item>Open-ſhake.</item>
                        <item>Shaked Beat.</item>
                        <item>Shaked Back-fall.</item>
                        <item>Shaked Elevation.</item>
                        <item>Shaked Cadent.</item>
                        <item>Double Relliſh.</item>
                        <item>exp.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52084:13"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Beat. exp: Backfall exp: Double-Backfall exp: elevation. <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>exp Spinger. exp: Cadent. exp: Backfall Shaked exp: <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>Close Shake. exp: Shaked Beat. exp: elevation exp: <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>Cadent. exp: Double. Relish exp: or thus: exp: For theſe, I am obliged to the ever famous Charles Colman Doctor in Muſick</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To theſe may be added the <hi>Gruppo, Trillo,</hi> or any other Movement of the Voyce imitated on the Viol, by playing the like-moving Notes with one motion of the Bow.</p>
                     <p>Of theſe fore-mentioned Graces, ſome are more rough and Maſculine, as your <hi>Shaked Beats</hi> and <hi>Back-falls,</hi> and therefore more peculiar to the <hi>Baſs;</hi> Others, more ſmooth and Feminine, as your <hi>Cloſe-ſhake</hi> and plain Graces, which are more natural to the <hi>Treble,</hi> or upper parts. Yet when we would expreſs Life, Courage, or Cheerfulneſs upon the <hi>Treble,</hi> we do fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently uſe both <hi>Shaked Beats</hi> and <hi>Back-falls,</hi> as on the contrary, ſmooth and ſwelling Notes when we would expreſs Love, Sorrow, Compaſſion, or the like; and this, not only on the <hi>Treble,</hi> but ſometimes alſo upon the <hi>Baſs.</hi> And all theſe are concerned in our <hi>Diviſion-Viol,</hi> as imploying the whole Compaſs of the Scale, and acting by turns all the Parts therein contained.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Hand</hi> thus directed, we will now proceed to the <hi>Concords</hi> of <hi>Muſick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52084:13"/>
                  <head>SECOND PART.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 1.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Concords, or a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium of Deſcant.</head>
                     <p>ALthough our excellent Country-man Mr. <hi>Morley,</hi> in his <hi>Introduction to Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> doth take his ſight, and reckon his Concords from the Tenor, as the Holding Part to which He and the Muſicians of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times were accuſtomed to apply their Deſcant, in order to the <hi>Gregorian</hi> Muſick of the Church; yet here, for better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (as to our preſent purpoſe) I muſt propoſe unto you the Baſs, as the Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work or Foundation upon which all Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Compoſition is to be erected; and from it we are to reckon or compute all thoſe diſtances or Intervalls which we uſe in joyning Parts together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 2.</hi> Of Intervalls.</head>
                     <p>IN reference to Intervalls, we are firſt to conſider an Uniſon; that is, One and the ſame Sound; whether produced by one ſingle voyce, or divers voyces ſounding together in the ſame Tone; and is, in Muſick, as an Unite in Arithmetick, or as a Point or Centre in Geometry, not diviſible. As Sounds recede more or leſs from the Uniſon, ſo do they make greater or leſſer Intervalls. As namely, firſt, a Second, divided into Perfect and Imperfect. A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Second is called a Tone, and cannot (as ſome contend) be exactly ſplit in two equal halfs, as to proportion of Sound, but is by moſt Authors ſubdivided into Nine leſſer Segments or Comma's, two whereof are aſſigned to a Diaſchiſma; four to the leſſer, five to the greater Semitone: and the difference between theſe two Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitones or imperfect Seconds, they call an Apotome. Some more curious Obſervers of theſe Fractions will needs ſay, that a Tone wants ſomewhat of nine Comma's, and that the greater Semitone doth not altogether reach to five, nor the leſſer to four. But theſe and other like obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being leſs requiſite to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it ſufficeth to have mentioned them; leaving a further diſquiſition thereof to ſuch as find leiſure and pleaſure to ſearch into theſe nicer ſubtilties.</p>
                     <p>Next follows a Third comprehending the perfect or greater Third by the name of <hi>Ditonus,</hi> and the Imperfect or leſſer Third by the name of <hi>Seméditonus.</hi> And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52084:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>here it is obſervable, as alſo elſewhere, that the particle <hi>Semi</hi> or <hi>Seme</hi> doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the half of the whole, but a defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, which makes the Sound fall a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone ſhort of the more complete and perfect Intervall.</p>
                     <p>A Fourth is divided into the greater by the name of <hi>Tritone,</hi> which is a prohibited Intervall, and the leſſer by the name of <hi>Diateſſaron.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Fifth is divided into Perfect and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect; the former is called <hi>Diapente,</hi> the later <hi>Semediapente;</hi> a falſe Fifth.</p>
                     <p>A Sixth is divided into the greater Hexachord conſiſting of a <hi>Tone</hi> and <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente,</hi> and the leſſer Hexachord conſiſting of a <hi>Diapente</hi> and <hi>Hemitone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A Seventh is divided into the greater conſiſting of a <hi>Ditonus</hi> and <hi>Diapente,</hi> and the leſſer conſiſting of a <hi>Diapente</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditonus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Octave is divided into Perfect, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Diapaſon,</hi> and Imperfect called <hi>Semedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From theſe Intervalls ariſe thoſe Diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which we call <hi>Concords</hi> and <hi>Diſcords,</hi> in ſuch manner and order as you ſee in the following Scheme, where an Octave is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into twelve Semitones or Half-notes, ſuch as may be obſerved in the Stops of fretted Inſtruments, or the Keys of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>Hapſecord</hi> or <hi>Organ;</hi> where (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon no more ſubdiviſions than twelve are exhibited) no difference appears between a <hi>Tritone</hi> and a <hi>Semediapente,</hi> (each being a <hi>Semitone</hi> leſs than a perfect Fifth) though in practical Muſick their appearance be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, the one like a Fourth, the other like a Fifth, as you ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
                     <figure/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52084:14"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 3.</hi> Of the Concords.</head>
                     <p>COncords are theſe; a Third, a Fifth, a Sixth, an Eight, and their Octaves. All the reſt (with their Octaves) are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords. A Fourth, as it is an Intervall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Fifth and Eight in the two upper parts, may in that ſence be called a Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but Computed with the Baſs, it is a Diſcord.</p>
                     <p>Again, Concords are of two Sorts; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and Imperfect. Perfect are theſe, a Fifth and Eighth. Imperfect, are a Third and Sixth; which two laſt have yet another Diſtinction, to wit, a greater and a leſſer Third, as alſo a greater and a leſſer Sixth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 4.</hi> Paſſage of the Concords.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt, take notice that two Perfects of the ſame kind, as two Fifths, or two Eights, riſing or falling together, is not allowed in Compoſition; but if the Notes ſtand ſtill in the ſame place, or if one of the parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move into the Octave it is allowed. Or if the parts remove in contrary motion, it may be allowed in Songs of many parts, as thus,</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Illicita <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Illicita <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Licita <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Licita <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Licita in pluribus partibus</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 5 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 5 5 8 8 8 8 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 5 5 5 8 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 8 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 8 8 8 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 5 5 5 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Not allowed Not allowed Allowed Allowed Allowed in many parts</p>
                     <p>But you may paſs from a Fifth to an Eighth, or from an Eighth to a Fifth, when you pleaſe; provided that one of the Parts either keep its place, or remove but one degree: For if both Parts leap together, the paſſage is leſs pleaſing.</p>
                     <p>As for Thirds and Sixths, which are Imperfect Concords, two, three, or more of them riſing or falling together, is no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loeciſme in Muſick.</p>
                     <p>In fine, you have liberty to paſs from any one, to any other different Concord, provided you avoyd <hi>Relation inharmonical;</hi> that is, a harſh and unpleaſing reflection of Flat againſt Sharp.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52084:15"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 5.</hi> Concerning the Key or Tone.</head>
                     <p>EVery Compoſition in Muſick, be it long or ſhort, is (or ought to be) deſigned to ſome one Key or Tone, in which the Baſs doth always conclude. This Key or Tone is called Flat or Sharp, according as the Key-note hath the leſſer or greater Third next above it. If it be the Leſſer Third, 'tis called a Flat Key; if the Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Third, 'tis a Sharp Key, thus exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Flat <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> Sharp</p>
                     <p>How ſtrange or difficult ſoever ſome Songs may appear by reaſon of the Flats or Sharps ſet at the beginning of them, yet all is but in relation to the Leſſer or Greater Third taking place next above the Key or Tone-Note; being the very ſame, in all reſpects, with the firſt Inſtances of the Leſſer and Greater Third above <hi>G.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As the Baſs is Flat or Sharp, ſo muſt the other Parts be ſet, which are joyned to it.</p>
                     <p>All theſe things will beſt appear in Counterpoint; that is, when we ſet the Notes of the higher Parts, Note for Note, juſt over the Notes of the Baſs, which (to a Beginner) is the eaſieſt way of ſhewing the uſe of the Concords. But firſt I muſt direct you</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52084:15"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 6.</hi> How to frame a Baſs.</head>
                     <p>IN making a Baſs three things muſt be obſerved; Firſt, that it be natural to the Key deſigned, making its middle Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (if it have any) in ſuch other Keys as have dependence upon the ſaid Key; ſuch are the Fifth and Third, if it be a flat Key; but if it be a ſharp, imploying the greater Third (which is not ſo proper and eaſie for a middle Cloſe) you may in ſtead thereof make uſe of the Fourth or Second above the final Key, in this manner.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 3 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 5 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 4 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 2</p>
                     <p>Secondly, let your Baſs move for the moſt part by Leaps of a Third, Fourth, or Fifth; uſing degrees no more than to keep it within the proper bounds and Ayre of the Key.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, I would have you (for more eaſe) to make choice of a Flat Key to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with, and avoid ſetting of ſharp Notes in it for ſome reaſons which will appear hereafter.</p>
                     <p>Let this ſhort Baſs ſerve for an Example, which hath a middle Cloſe in <hi>B</hi> the Flat third to the Key.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 7.</hi> How to joyn a Treble to the Baſs.</head>
                     <p>ABaſs being prick'd, you may joyn a Treble to it by ſetting like Notes a Third, Fifth, or Eighth above it. As for Sixths (which properly belong to ſharp Notes) I ſhall ſpeak of them hereafter. Now, as the proper movement of the Baſs in Counterpoint, is (for the moſt part) by Leaps, ſo the natural progreſſion of the Treble is a riſing and falling by degrees: and therefore, when you have ſet a Third, Fifth or Eighth over the firſt Note of the Baſs, you may take for your next, (and ſo from one to another) that Concord which affords the neareſt Compliance to that movement by degrees, as you ſee in the Example. If you ſet a figure under each Note as you prick it, to ſignifie what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord it bears to the Baſs, as you here ſee them, it will be ſome eaſe to your Eye and Memory.</p>
                     <p>Take notice that in few Parts Imperfect Concords are more delightful than Perfect, as not ſatiating or cloying the Ear ſo much as the multiplicity of Perfects do. Hence it is that in Two parts we ſeldom uſe Eights, unleſs to the Beginning-Note, Ending-Note,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52084:16"/>Cadent-Notes, or where the Parts proceed in contrary motion; that is, one aſcending and the other deſcending.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 8.</hi> Compoſition of three Parts.</head>
                     <p>WHen you are perfect in ſetting a <hi>Treble</hi> and <hi>Baſs,</hi> you may add to them a third Part, as for inſtance, an <hi>Alt,</hi> whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per region is next under the Treble; and therefore I would have you ſet it (Note for Note) in thoſe Concords which are neareſt thereto. Provided, that if you intend your Compoſition for no more than three Parts, one of the two upper Parts be ſtill a Third to the Baſs, for the reaſon above-mentioned.</p>
                     <p>I have made the <hi>Treble</hi> and <hi>Alt</hi> both of them end in the Eight to the <hi>Baſs,</hi> which in my opinion is better (the Key being flat) than to have the <hi>Treble</hi> end in the ſharp Third; that Concord being more proper to ſome inward Part at a Concluſion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cantus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>3 5 3 5 3 5 3 5 8 <hi>Altus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>8 3 8 3 8 3 8 3 8 <hi>Baſſus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Concerning thoſe two Notes which you ſee made ſharp in the <hi>Alt,</hi> take notice, that when the <hi>Baſs</hi> aſcends a Fourth, or deſcends a Fifth, it commonly requires the ſharp or greater Third to that Note from which it ſo riſeth or falleth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 9.</hi> Compoſition of four Parts.</head>
                     <p>BEing perfect in compoſing of Three Parts, you may try how you can add to them a Fourth Part, which now remains to be the <hi>Tenor;</hi> concerning which, theſe things are to be obſerved. (1.) That it be ſet (as much as may be) in Concords dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the other two upper Parts. (2.) That it be ſet as neer as you can to the <hi>Alt;</hi> for the Melody is beſt when the upper Parts are joyned cloſe one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. (3.) That you avoid the Conſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two Fifts, or two Eights, riſing or falling together; as well amongſt the upper Parts themſelves, as betwixt any one Part and the <hi>Baſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All which is at once performed by taking the next Concord, Note for Note, which you find under the <hi>Alt.</hi> As appears by the following Example.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52084:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cantus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>3 5 3 5 3 5 5 3 5 8 <hi>Altus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>8 3 8 3 8 3 3 8 3 8 <hi>Tenor.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 8 5 8 5 8 8 5 8 3 <hi>Baſſus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have broken the laſt Note but one of the <hi>Alt,</hi> into two <hi>Crochets,</hi> and joyned one of them to the Note before it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it, by that means, a Binding-Cadence; which you may imitate upon the like Notes, in that Part always which bears the ſharp or greater Third to the <hi>Baſs</hi> in the next Note before any Cloſe.</p>
                     <p>Though for eaſe and order's ſake I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you firſt how to joyn one part to your Baſs, then two, and laſtly three, by ſetting and adding one part after another; yet now it is left to your liberty to carry on all your upper parts (ſo many as you deſign) together, diſpoſing them into ſuch Concords as you think moſt Convenient: Provided that one of the parts be ſtill a Third to the Baſs, which in Compoſition of three or more parts, ſhould never be omitted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 10.</hi> Concerning a Sixth.</head>
                     <p>IF your Baſs have ſharp Notes in it (ſuch are commonly the Half Note under the Key or Tone, the greater Third above it, and ſometimes alſo the leſſer Third under it:) Notes ſtanding in theſe places do common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly require a Sixth to be joyned to them, as you ſee in this Example.</p>
                     <p>Here you have three Notes in the Baſs, which require the leſſer Sixth to be joyned to them; The Firſt in <hi>E.</hi> (the leſſer Third under the Key) whoſe Sixt is in the Treble. The Second in <hi>F</hi> Sharp (the half Note un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Key) whoſe Sixth is in the Tenor. The Third in <hi>B.</hi> Sharp (the greater Third above the Key) whoſe Sixth is in the Alt. Concerning which ſome things are to be Noted.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, That when the Sixth is uſed, the Fifth muſt be left out; for a Fift and Sixth muſt not ſound together in Counterpoint. Secondly, That the Half-Note under the Key, doth hardly admit an Eight to be joyned to it, without offence to a Critical Ear; and therefore have I put two parts in the ſame Third, as you ſee in the firſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52084:17"/>Bar, rather than have any part to ſound in the Eighth to that Sharp Note in <hi>F.</hi> Thirdly, That Baſſes, conſiſting much of Notes requiring a Sixth, are more apt for few than for many Parts. Fourthly, That the Baſs, in ſuch kind of Notes, doth want a Third of its full Latitude or Compaſs; as is evident in this, that if you do but remove the ſaid Sharp Notes a Third lower, thoſe Sixths are changed in Eights, the Thirds into Fifts, and the Sharp prohibited Eight into a Third, as in the Example following. And thus you ſee where Sixths are uſed, and how they may be avoided when you deſire it.</p>
                     <p>From hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that ſeeing a Fifth and Sixth are never uſed together in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoint, it conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follows that there can be but three ſeveral Concords (which are a Third, a Fifth or Sixth, and an Eighth) joyned at once to any one Note of the Baſs. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you have a mind to compoſe more parts than four, (as five, ſix, ſeven, or eight parts) it muſt be done by redoubling thoſe Concords in their Octaves, and making the parts paſs into different changes to avoid the Conſecution of Fifts and Eights, which duely obſerved, your Compoſition (no doubt) will be Harmonions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cantus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>3 8 5 3 3 5 8 3 5 3 <hi>Altus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>8 5 3 8 8 8 5 8 3 8 <hi>Tenor.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 3 8 5 5 3 3 5 8 5 <hi>Baſſus.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 11.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Diſcords.</head>
                     <p>DIſcords are two wayes admitted into Muſick: Firſt, in Diminution; that is, when two, three, four, or more Notes of one Part, are ſet againſt one Note of a different Part: In which poſition a Diſcord is allowed to any Note of the Diminution, except the Leading Note, which ſhould alwayes be a Concord. Example</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 4 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 6 7 8 7 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 8 7 6 5 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 3 4 5 6 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>3 4 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 5 4 5 6</p>
                     <p>Here obſerve, that two, three, four, or more Notes ſtanding together in the ſame Rule or Space, may be conſidered as one intire Note; and may admit the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Diſcord to any of them, the firſt, only excepted. Example.</p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52084:17"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>7 6 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 5 4 3 2 3 8 7 5 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>8 2 3 4 5 6</p>
                     <p>The other way in which <hi>Diſcords</hi> are not only allowed, but of moſt excellent uſe, is in <hi>Syncopation</hi> or <hi>Binding;</hi> that is, when a Note of One Part ends and breaks off upon the Middle of the Note of an other Part, as you ſee in the following Examples.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Syncopation in two Parts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>876 6543 4676 8 3 4 3 4343 238 323 2323 2346438 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5676 7676 76765 4 38 343 43238 8 76 53656 765 4 38 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Syncopation in three Parts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 6 7 6 85 6 7 65 7 6 8 3 65 3 65 3 65 4 3 8 5656 5656 7 6 5 8 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>323 3 3 3 4 3 3 3 3 3 843 843 843 8 3 3 3 3 434 3 4 3 8</p>
                     <p>In this way of <hi>Binding,</hi> a <hi>Diſcord</hi> may be applyed to the firſt part of any Note of the <hi>Baſs,</hi> if the other part of the Bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Note did ſound in Concord to that Note which went before.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52084:18"/>
                     <p>Diſcords thus admitted, we are next to conſider how they are brought off, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them delightful to the Ear; for ſimply of themſelves they are harſh and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and introduced into Muſick for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety; or, by ſtriking the ſenſe with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionate Sound, to beget attention to that which follows; to the hearing of which, the Ear is carried on (as it were) by a neceſſary expectation.</p>
                     <p>This winding or bringing a diſcord off, is beſt effected by changing from thence into ſome imperfect Concord, to which more ſweetneſs is added by the Diſcord go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before. Yet here the Ear is not fully ſatisfied until theſe Diſcords and Imperfect Concords arrive at One more perfect, where (as at a period) we underſtand the ſenſe of that which went before. Now, in paſſing from Diſcords to Imperfects; or from Imperfects to Perfects, the Rule ſhould be this; that we deflect to that which is neareſt rather than to one more remote: Hence it is that the greater Sixth is obſerved (by <hi>Des Cartes</hi>) to paſs more naturally into an Eighth, and the leſſer Sixth into a Fifth. This little remove, by a Tone or Semitone, connects and makes ſmooth the Ayre of the Muſick in paſſing from Concord to Concord; which, by a greater remove, would rather ſeem disjointed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 12.</hi> Of the exceſſive Fourth, and Defective Fifth.</head>
                     <p>ALthough an Exceſſive Fourth and Defective Fifth be Diſcords, yet are they of moſt excellent uſe in all Figurate Muſick, and are ſometimes ſet without Syncope or Binding, which (according to the Rules of Compoſition) is not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to other Diſcords. Either of them conſiſts of ſix Semitones, which ſeems the ſame, as to proportion of Sound; But here we muſt conſider them as they are repreſented to the Eye, like a Fourth and a Fifth, which (if you place one above the other) compleat the Compaſs of an <hi>Octave,</hi> thus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Semidiapente Tritone Tritonus. Semidiapente.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A <hi>Tritone</hi> naturally paſſeth into a Sixth, a <hi>Semidiapente</hi> into a Third.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Tritonus. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Semidiapente.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52084:18"/>
                     <p>A defective Fifth doth naturally require a Sixth to be joyned with it, as you ſee it ſet in the Example; which perhaps may ſeem a contradiction to what I ſaid (<hi>pag.</hi> 19.) that a Fifth and Sixth muſt not ſound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that is, as Concords ſet Note againſt Note without binding: But this Fifth ſtands as a Diſcord, and is back'd with a Sixth to mollifie its harſhneſs: For (as I have formerly ſaid) there can be but Three Concords joyned at once to the Baſs, which are alwayes (except when a Sixth takes place) a Third, Fifth, and Eight. And therefore if a Hundred or Hundred Thouſand Voices were joyned together in Muſical Concordance, they muſt all ſound in theſe Three Concords or in their Octaves, which is ſtill but the ſame ſpecies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 13.</hi> Reflections upon the Concords of Muſick.</head>
                     <p>ANd here I cannot but wonder, even to amazement, that from no more than Three Concords, (with ſome intervening Diſcords) there ſhould ariſe ſuch an infinite variety, as all the Muſick that ever has been or ever ſhall be compoſed. And my wonder is encreaſed by a conſideration of the Seven Gradual Sounds or Tones, from whoſe various poſitions and Intermixtures thoſe Concords and Diſcords do ariſe. Theſe Gradual Sounds are diſtinguiſhed in the Scale of Muſick by the ſame ſeven Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which in the Kalender diſtinguiſh the ſeven dayes of the Week; to either of which, the adding of more is but a repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the former over again.</p>
                     <p>This Myſterious number of ſeven, leads me into a contemplation of the Univerſe, whoſe Creation is deliver'd unto our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity (not without ſome myſtery) as begun and finiſhed in ſeven dayes, which is thought to be figured long ſince by <hi>Orpheus</hi> his ſeven ſtringed Lyre. Within the Circumference of this great Univerſe, be ſeven Globes or Spherical Bodies in continual Motion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing ſtill new and various figures, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their divers poſitions one to another. When with theſe I compare my ſeven Gradual Sounds, I cannot but admire the Reſemblance of their Harmonies, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the one ſo exactly anſwering to the Aſpects of the other; as an Uniſon to a Conjunction, an Octave to an Oppoſition; the middle Conſonants in a Diapaſon, to the middle Aſpects in an Orb; as a Third, Fifth, Sixth, in Muſick, to a Trine, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, Sextile in the Zodiack. And as theſe by moving into ſuch and ſuch Aſpects tranſmit their Influences into Elementary Bodies; So thoſe, by paſſing into ſuch and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52084:19"/>ſuch Concords, tranſmit into the Ear an Influence of Sound, which doth not only ſtrike the ſenſe, but even aſſect the very ſoul, ſtirring it up to a devout Contemplation of that Divine PRINCIPLE from whence all Harmony proceeds; and therefore very fitly applyed to ſing and ſound forth his Glory and Praiſe.</p>
                     <p>When I further conſider that Three Sounds placed by the Interval of a Third one above another, do conſtitute one entire Harmony, which governs and compriſes all the Sounds which by Art or Imagination can, at once, be joyned together in Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Concordance; This I cannot but think a ſignificant Embleme of that Supreme and incomprehenſible THREE in ONE, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning, Compriſing and Diſpoſing the whole Machine of the world with all its included parts, in a moſt perfect and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peadious Harmony.</p>
                     <p>I inſiſt not upon things of common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, as that a String being ſtruck, the like String of another Inſtrument (tuned in Concordance to it) ſhould alſo ſound and move; or that the Sound of a Sackbot, Trumpet, or like extended <hi>Tube,</hi> ſhould, by a Stronger emiſſion of the Breath, skip from Concord to Concord before you can force it into any gradation of Tones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What I have already mention'd is enough to perſuade me that there is a greater myſterie in the Harmony of Sounds, than what hath been yet diſcovered.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 14.</hi> The Analogy of Muſical Concords to the Aſpects of the Planets, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in the following Scheme.</head>
                     <p>WHere you have the ſeven Gradual Sounds in their orderly progreſſion repreſented on the Diameter-line. Upon which, is alſo deſcribed a <hi>Diapaſon</hi> with its included Conſonants, according to the Arithmetical diviſion thereof, as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally found upon a Monochord, or the String of any fretted Inſtrument, from the Nut to the middle thereof. The outmoſt Circle repreſents the Zodiack, and the Aſpects of the Planets, to which you ſee the <hi>Diapaſon</hi> with its Interſections exactly agreeing; as <hi>viz.</hi> The two Terms thereof, to a Conjunction and Oppoſition; The middle Section (which generates a Fifth on one ſide, and a Fourth on the other) to a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>. A Third and a Sixth compleating alſo the Compaſs of an Octave, as a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> and * do a Semicircle or the two oppoſite points of an Orbe. To which may be added, that a <hi>Diapaſon</hi> is divided into Twelve Semitones, as the Zodiack into Twelve Signes or Sections.</p>
                     <p>The other Figure ſhews, that all the Sounds that can poſſibly be joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Muſical Concordance, are ſtill but the reiterated Harmony of Three.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52084:19"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram demonstrating the analogy of music and the zodiacal planets</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram demonstrating the analogy of music and the holy trinity</figDesc>
                        <q>Benedicta sit ſancta et individua Trinitas</q>
                     </figure>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:52084:20"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52084:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The DIVISION-VIOL,</hi> OR The Art of Playing <hi>ex tempore</hi> to a GROUND. THIRD PART.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 1.</hi> Of Diviſion, and the manner of performing it.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DIminution</hi> or <hi>Diviſion to a Ground,</hi> is the Breaking, either of the <hi>Baſs,</hi> or of any higher Part that is applyable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. The manner of expreſſing it is thus:</p>
                     <p>A <hi>Ground, Subject,</hi> or <hi>Baſs,</hi> (call it which you pleaſe) is prick'd down in two ſeveral Papers: One for him who is to play the <hi>Ground</hi> upon an <hi>Organ, Harpſechord,</hi> or what other Inſtrument may be apt for that purpoſe; the Other, for him that plays upon the <hi>Viol,</hi> who, having the ſaid <hi>Ground</hi> before his eyes, as his <hi>Theme</hi> or <hi>Subject,</hi> plays ſuch variety of <hi>Deſcant</hi> or <hi>Diviſion</hi> in Concordance thereto, as his skill and preſent invention do then ſuggeſt unto him. In this manner of Play, which is the perfection of the <hi>Viol,</hi> or any other Inſtrument, if it be exactly performed, a man may ſhew the Excellency both of his Hand and Invention, to the delight and admiration of thoſe that hear him.</p>
                     <p>But this you will ſay is a perfection that few attain unto, depending much upon the quickneſs of Invention as well as quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Hand. I anſwer, it is a perfection which ſome excellent Hands have not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto, as wanting thoſe helps which ſhould lead them to it; the ſupply of which want is the buſineſs we here endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. True it is, that Invention is a gift of Nature, but much improved by Exerciſe and Practice. He that hath it not in ſo high a meaſure as to play <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> to a <hi>Ground,</hi> may, notwithſtanding give both himſelf and hearers ſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in playing ſuch Diviſions as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or others have made for that purpoſe; in the performance whereof he may deſerve the Name of an excellent Artiſt; for here the excellency of the Hand may be ſhewed as well as in the Other, and the Muſick perhaps better, though leſs to be admired, as being more ſtudied. But to our matter in hand:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52084:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 2.</hi> Several kinds of Diviſion.</head>
                     <p>IN Playing to a <hi>Ground</hi> we exerciſe the whole Compaſs of the <hi>Viol,</hi> acting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſometimes the Part of a <hi>Baſs,</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Treble</hi> or ſome other Part. From hence proceed Two kinds of Diviſion, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Breaking of the Ground,</hi> and a <hi>Deſcanting upon it:</hi> Out of which two, is generated a Third ſort of Diviſion; to wit a <hi>Mixture</hi> of Thoſe, one with the other; which Third or laſt ſort, is expreſſed in a two fold Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; that is, either in Single or in Double Notes.</p>
                     <p>Theſe ſeveral ſorts of Diviſion are uſed upon the <hi>Baſs-Viol,</hi> very promiſcuouſly, according to the Fancy of the Player or Compoſer; Howbeit, for Order and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods ſake, I muſt diſcourſe of them ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; and will begin with.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 3.</hi> Breaking the Ground.</head>
                     <p>BReaking the <hi>Ground</hi> is the <hi>dividing its Notes into more diminute Notes.</hi> As for inſtance, a <hi>Semibreve</hi> may be broken into two <hi>Minims,</hi> foure <hi>Crochets,</hi> eight <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> ſixteen <hi>Semiquavers, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Breaking or Dividing a Note admits divers ways of expreſſion, according to the divers ordering and diſpoſing the Minute parts thereof.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Five ways of Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Note.</note> when there is no variation of Sound, by reaſon of the <hi>Minutes</hi> ſtanding ſtill in the ſame place, or removing into the <hi>Octave,</hi> which I accompt it but the ſame Tone.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, when the Sound is varyed, and yet the Ayre retained, either by a quick return, or by keeping near to the place of the Note divided: thus:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52084:21"/>
                     <p>Thirdly, when the <hi>Minute</hi> Notes are imployed in making a Tranſition to the next Note of the <hi>Ground;</hi> as you ſee in the following Examples, where Notes are broken to all the ſeveral diſtances in an <hi>Octave,</hi> both aſcending and deſcending.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>3 4 5 6 7 8 <hi>Aſcending.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcending</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 <hi>Aſcending.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcending</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>2 3 4 5 6 <hi>Aſcending.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcending.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>7 8 2 3 4 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 6 7 8 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ascending</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Descending</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have ſet ſome part of the Example in a higher <hi>Cliff,</hi> becauſe this Breaking a Note by way of Tranſition, holds good in higher Parts as well as in the <hi>Baſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52084:22"/>
                     <p>Fourthly, when the <hi>Minutes</hi> are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in ſkipping into other <hi>Concords,</hi> as you ſee in breaking theſe four <hi>Semibreves.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>853 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 468 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 85635 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 853468 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 853</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, when the ſaid <hi>Minutes</hi> make a <hi>Gradual</hi> Tranſition into ſome of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, paſſing from thence, either to end in the Sound of the<note n="*" place="margin">Holding-Note, Standing-Note, Ground-Note, and Note divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>are the ſame.</hi>
                        </note> Holding Note, or elſe, moving on, to meet the next Note of the <hi>Ground.</hi> And though this moving into the Concords, be the very ſame as Deſcant, ſo long as it continues in that Motion; yet in regard of its returning either to its <hi>own Note,</hi> or to meet the <hi>next following Note</hi> in nature of a Baſs, we muſt <hi>here</hi> rank it under the name and notion of Breaking the Ground. The manner of it you may ſee in theſe following Inſtances.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Theſe paſs up to the 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Theſe to the 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to a 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> higher Theſe to a 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> higher.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Theſe to a 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Theſe to a 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to an 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Theſe to a 3.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> higher</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>2 <hi>Theſe paſs to the 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Theſe to a 6.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Theſe to the 8.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> below Theſe into Concords both above and below.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The chief Myſterie of Diviſion to a Ground may be referred to theſe three Heads.<note place="margin">How <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is made har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious to the <hi>Holding-Note</hi> of the <hi>Ground.</hi>
                        </note> Firſt, That it be harmonious to the holding Note. Secondly, That it come off ſo, as to meet the next Note of the <hi>Ground</hi> in a ſmooth and natural paſſage. Thirdly, Or if it paſs into Diſcords, that they be ſuch as are aptly uſed in Compoſition.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>As thus. Exemp: Gratiâ.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>This paſses into a 4.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> This into a 7.<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:52084:22"/>
                     <p>How Diviſion is made harmonious to the Holding-Note, was ſhewed in the Fifth way of breaking a Note. And the Bringing it off to meet the next Note of the <hi>Ground,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">How <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is brought off to Meet the next <hi>Note</hi> of the <hi>Ground.</hi>
                        </note> is much after the ſame way, <hi>viz.</hi> by making the laſt three, or more of the Minute Notes (at leaſt two of them) aſcend or deſcend by degrees, unto the next ſucceeding Note, as you ſee here following where the <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breve</hi> in <hi>G.</hi> is broken to all the diſtances in an <hi>Octave.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>As thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> or thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> or thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> or thus</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Thus <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> or thus &amp;c:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>This holds good, be the Diviſion quicker or ſlower; Onely that in quick Diviſion more of the minutes will offer themſelves in making this <hi>Gradual</hi> tranſition to the ſucceeding Note, as you ſee in the <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quavers</hi> of the precedent Inſtances.</p>
                     <p>By this which hath been ſhewed, you ſee (I ſuppoſe) what belongs to Breaking a Note: but this requires not only a Notion but a Habit alſo, which muſt be got by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Wherefore I would have you prick down ſome eaſy <hi>Ground;</hi> and break each Note making a Tranſition ſtill from Note to Note, according to what hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. To the better effecting whereof, I will ſet you an Example, with which take theſe Advertiſements.</p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52084:23"/>
                     <p>Firſt, That your Diviſion be carried on ſmoothly, as we have formerly admoniſhed; and that your <hi>Flats</hi> and <hi>Sharps</hi> have ſtill relation to the Key and Ayre of your <hi>Ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, you are to conſider that a Seventh or Sixth falling, is the ſame as a Second or Third riſing, and ſo you may conſider all other diſtances, with their oppoſite <hi>Octaves.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>2 3 4 5 6 7 8 8 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>7 6 5 4 3 2 8</p>
                     <p>And therefore you may chooſe whether you will meet, any ſucceeding Note of the <hi>Ground,</hi> in the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſon,</hi> or in its <hi>Octave,</hi> above or below it; for, concerning <hi>Octaves</hi> the reaſon is ſtill the ſame.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, in ſuch places as the <hi>Ground</hi> doth intimate a Cadence, by falling a Fifth or riſing a Fourth; all the Notes that hit upon the Third above, or Sixth below, muſt be played Sharp. <hi>See Pag.</hi> 18.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">How <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is to Move be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Ground-Note.</hi>
                        </note> as your Diviſion paſſes into the Third and Fifth, whilſt it moveth above (by which it is made harmonious to the to the <hi>Ground-Note</hi>) ſo, in moving beneath, it muſt paſs into the under <hi>Octaves</hi> of thoſe Concords, <hi>viz.</hi> into the Sixth and Fourth below the <hi>Ground-Note.</hi> Thus</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>535 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 535 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 535 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>464 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 464 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 464</p>
                     <p>Theſe things being known, you may break your <hi>Ground</hi> in ſuch manner as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; where you have the Diviſion placed over the <hi>Ground,</hi> that you may better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the breaking of each Note.</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52084:23"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Example of Breaking the Ground</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52084:24"/>
                     <p>Here you ſee every Note of the <hi>Ground</hi> broken, according to ſome One or Other of thoſe five ways before-mentioned; only I have made the <hi>Diviſion,</hi> in one place, to meet the <hi>Ground-Note</hi> in the Third; and in another place in the Fifth: both which are mark'd out unto you for your imitation, when the Point, or any other convenience ſhall invite you thereunto.</p>
                     <p>Here a doubt may ariſe, concerning the <hi>Seventh</hi> above and <hi>Second</hi> below the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded-Note;</hi> which, in the <hi>Diviſion,</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made Sharp, and ſuddenly Flat again, according to its own nature: in which doubts the Ear muſt always be chief Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. Howbeit, in this particular, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (I think) may be deliver'd by way of Rule; which is, that if we deſcend to a Second, and immediately aſcend again, that Second muſt be made Sharp: The ſame is underſtood of the Seventh above, in reference to the Eighth, as you may ſee in breaking the two <hi>Semibreves</hi> in <hi>D.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here your Ear will tell you that the Note in <hi>C</hi> requires a Sharp: but in the ſecond Inſtance where the next Note doth not ſo aſcend, no Sharp is required.</p>
                     <p>From this Rule we muſt except, that if the <hi>Ground</hi> do ſuddenly riſe or fall to a Flat Second; or fall a Third, or make a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: In theſe Caſes no Sharp is required, though the Note riſe again, as you may ſee in theſe Inſtances.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Another obſervation is; that at a <hi>Cloſe</hi> I would always have the <hi>Diviſion</hi> to end in the Sound of the Note next before the <hi>Cloſe,</hi> and from thence leap off into the Sound of the Final Note, as you ſee it doth in all the Strains of the laſt Example. And here I cannot but take notice of an error which I have obſerved in ſome reputed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Violiſts; who in playing a <hi>Conſort-Baſs,</hi> would ſometimes at the very <hi>Cloſe,</hi> run down by degrees to the Concluding-Note; than which nothing is more improper: for, if any <hi>upper Part</hi> do fall from a Fifth to an Eighth (a thing moſt frequent) the <hi>Baſs,</hi> by ſuch a Running down by degrees, doth make two prohibited Eights to the ſaid Part.</p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52084:24"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Not allowed. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Not allowed. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Allowed. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Allowed.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>5 8 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 88 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 88 <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Illicita. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Illicita. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Licita. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Licita.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Though this Running down by degrees, be worſe in playing a <hi>Conſort-Baſs,</hi> than in <hi>Diviſion to a Ground;</hi> yet in This alſo it doth not want its bad conſequence; the <hi>Organiſt</hi> commonly joyning ſuch Parts to his <hi>Ground,</hi> as the <hi>Compoſer</hi> doth unto his Baſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 4.</hi> Deſcant Diviſion.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DEſcant Diviſion</hi> is that which makes a Different-concording-part unto the <hi>Ground.</hi> It differs from the Former in Theſe particulars. That breaks the Notes of the <hi>Ground;</hi> This Deſcants upon them. That takes the liberty to wander ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times beneath the <hi>Ground;</hi> This (as in its proper ſphere) moves ſtill above it. That meets every ſucceeding Note of the <hi>Ground,</hi> in the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſon</hi> or <hi>Octave;</hi> This, in any of the <hi>Concords.</hi> But in the main buſineſs of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> they are much the ſame: for all <hi>Diviſion,</hi> whether <hi>Deſcant</hi> or <hi>Breaking</hi> the <hi>Baſs,</hi> is but a Tranſition from Note to Note, or from one Concord to another, either by Degrees or Leaps, with an Intermixture of ſuch Diſcords as are allowed in Compoſition.</p>
                     <p>The Rules of <hi>Deſcant-Diviſion</hi> are the ſame I gave you in joyning another Part to your <hi>Baſs;</hi> That is, you may begin with a Third, Fifth or Eighth to the <hi>Ground-Note;</hi> paſſing on to meet the next Note alſo in a Third, Fifth, or Eighth: provided you avoyd the conſecution of Perfects of the ſame kind, as hath been delivered. The manner of Breaking this <hi>Deſcant</hi> is the ſame I gave you in Breaking a <hi>Note,</hi> according to thoſe Five Ways mentioned <hi>pag.</hi> 28. and left to your liberty to uſe This or That, as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
                     <p>A <hi>Diſcord</hi> is never uſed to the Beginning of the <hi>Ground-Note,</hi> unleſs in <hi>Syncope,</hi> as hath been ſhewed. A <hi>Sext</hi> is ſeldome uſed as the <hi>Leading-Note,</hi> unleſs in Binding, or to ſuch Notes as require a <hi>Sext:</hi> not only Sharp Notes requiring the leſſer <hi>Sext,</hi> as was ſhewed <hi>pag.</hi> 19. but ſometimes alſo Flat Notes which require the greater <hi>Sixth</hi>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:52084:25"/>in ſtead of the <hi>Fift,</hi> as you ſee in the middle Bar of the Example following; in which, the black Notes expreſs the full latitude of the <hi>Baſs,</hi> according to what hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſhewed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>6 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 66 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 6 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 6 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 6<gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, if you do but break this <hi>Ground</hi> according to the black Notes, you will find that your <hi>Diviſion</hi> doth (of it ſelf) produce Sixths to thoſe Notes which ſtand a Third higher.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>6 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 6 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 6</p>
                     <p>And here you may perceive the reaſon, why ſuch Notes affect a Sixth and not a Fifth, becauſe a Fifth would produce a Seventh to thoſe Notes which expreſs the full latitude of the <hi>Baſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 5.</hi> Mixt Diviſion.</head>
                     <p>I Call that <hi>Mixt Diviſion</hi> which mixeth <hi>Deſcant</hi> and <hi>Breaking the Ground,</hi> one with the other; under which name I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all <hi>Diviſion</hi> which preſents to our Ears the Sounds of <hi>Two</hi> or more Parts moving together: And, this is expreſſed either in ſingle Notes, by hitting firſt upon One String and then upon an Other; or in double Notes, by touching two or more Strings at once with the Bow. This, as it is more excellent than the ſingle ways of Breaking the <hi>Ground,</hi> or Deſcanting upon it, ſo it is more intricate, and requires more of judgment and skill in Compoſition; by reaſon of the Bindings and intermixtures of Diſcords, which are as frequent in This as in any other <hi>Figurate Muſick.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:52084:25"/>
                     <p>I will give you Examples of This and of <hi>Deſcant-Diviſion;</hi> not inſiſting upon the ſeveral diſtances in an Octave (now leſs needfull) but upon ſuch paſſages as offer themſelves moſt remarkable in <hi>Grounds;</hi> ſuch are <hi>Cadences.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 6.</hi> Cadences of two ſorts.</head>
                     <p>THough <hi>Cadences</hi> may ſeem to be many in Number, yet in effect they are but Two; to wit, a Seventh brought off with a Sixth, after which the <hi>Baſs</hi> falls a Tone or Semitone; or elſe, a Fourth brought off with a Third, after which the <hi>Baſs</hi> commonly falls a Fifth, or riſes a Fourth, which is the ſame thing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>76 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 76 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 43 <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> 43</p>
                     <p>Your firſt Example ſhall be upon the firſt ſort of <hi>Cadence,</hi> and the Notes leading to it: in which you have firſt, the <hi>Ground</hi> broken; then <hi>Deſcant;</hi> and laſtly, <hi>Mixt Diviſion,</hi> both in ſingle and double Notes; by which you may better diſcern how they differ one from another.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Minuritio</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ground Broken.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fundamentalis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Simplex.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Deſcant.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Melothetica.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Compoſita.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mixt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mixta.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:52084:26"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Example upon the first ſort of Cadence.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In Playing to a <hi>Ground</hi> we do ſometimes for humour or variety hold out One Note of <hi>Deſcant</hi> to two or three Notes of the <hi>Ground</hi> (ſuch as will bear it) as you ſee in the firſt variation of <hi>Deſcant</hi> in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, where you may alſo behold a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth brought off with a Sixth, which paſſes into its deſired Eighth. In the other Variations of <hi>Deſcant</hi> you have the figure [6] ſet under thoſe Notes which lead the <hi>Diviſion</hi> anſwering to that Note of the <hi>Ground</hi> which require a Sixth. Laſtly, you may obſerve, that ſometimes part of the Laſt or Concluding Note is alſo divided, which is left to the liberty of the Player or Compoſer.</p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:52084:26"/>
                     <p>Your next Example is the ſame <hi>Cadence</hi> Sharp, that you may perceive how great a difference of Ayre there is, betwixt the ſame Notes Flat &amp; Sharp; as upon hearing you might eaſily judge; though the ſame Diminution were applyed to each of them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Example upon the first ſort of Cadence Sharp</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:52084:27"/>
                     <p>We will now proceed to the other ſort of <hi>Cadence,</hi> which is a Fourth brought off with a Third; and firſt upon a <hi>Minim.</hi> Thus:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Example of the Second Sort of Cadence upon a Minim</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ground Broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Where obſerve, that if the Notes were played twice ſo ſlow or long as they are here ſet down, the Example would be a <hi>Cadence</hi> upon a <hi>Semibreve.</hi> Nevertheleſs, I will ſet your next upon a <hi>Semibreve;</hi> and, that I may compriſe ſomething more under the ſame Example, I will place four <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims</hi> before it; by which you may ſee how to divide Notes deſcending by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52084:27"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Example of the Second Sort of Cadence upon a Semibreve</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Descant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:52084:28"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 7</hi> Concerning Fifths and Eighths in Diviſion.</head>
                     <p>IN this laſt, and alſo in other Examples, there is one thing which may ſcandalize a young Compoſer, and perhaps give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to ſome old Critick, in prevention whereof I will ſpeak a little in this place. Every Compoſer knows that the Conſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fifths and Eighths, is not allowed in Muſick; that is, between two different Parts. Now when we Play Diviſion to a <hi>Ground,</hi> it is to be conſidered whether or no we Play a different Part from the ſaid <hi>Ground.</hi> I anſwer, in <hi>Deſcant</hi> Diviſion we do. But in dividing a <hi>Ground,</hi> we play but the ſame Part with it; in which doing, if we hit upon the Eighth <hi>above</hi> or <hi>below</hi> the <hi>Ground-Note</hi> (which will produce, ſometimes, two or more Eighths together, as you ſee in the firſt variation of the precedent Example) yet this is ſtill to be accompted as but one and the ſame Sound with the Baſs; and therefore if any man except againſt ſuch a Conſecution of Eighths, he may aſwel except againſt the Organ, Harpſecord, or Lute, having <hi>Octaves</hi> joyned to their Baſſes, which being ſtruck one after another, produce the conſequence of ſo many Eighths together.</p>
                     <p>As for Fifths, they cannot occur in Breaking the <hi>Ground,</hi> becauſe there we meet every following Note in the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſon</hi> or <hi>Oclave.</hi> If they happen in <hi>Deſcant,</hi> there is no Apology for them, except one of them be a falſe Fifth; which, though not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome preciſe Muſicians of former times, yet our more modern Authors, as well Writers as Compoſers, do both uſe it and approve it. For my own part, I do not only allow the Conſecution of <hi>Two Fifths,</hi> when one of them is Defective, but (being rightly taken) eſteem it amongſt the Elegancies of <hi>Figurate Muſick.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Your next Example is a <hi>Cadence</hi> upon a <hi>Breve,</hi> with four <hi>Minims</hi> aſcending to it by degrees.</p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:52084:28"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>An Example of the Second Sort of Cadence upon a Breve</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Descant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52084:29"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 8.</hi> Concerning Sixths and Thirds in Diviſion.</head>
                     <p>IN the mixt Diviſion of theſe Examples, you have in ſome places many Sixths ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken one after another, in other places ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thirds; concerning which, obſerve; that in Notes where we hit two Strings at once with the Bow, Thirds are more eaſie for the Hand, and more pleaſing to the Ear than many Sixths together: But, in Mixt Notes where we hit one String after another, Sixths are eſteemed better than Thirds; for, the Leaps of thoſe being greater, a greater variety is conveyed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ear. Thence it is, that in Skipping-Diviſion we rather make uſe of Tenths then ſimple Thirds, when there follow many of them one after another. Howbeit, if skipping Thirds be expreſs'd upon two different Strings they are very delightful in Mixt Diviſion.</p>
                     <p>Having ſpoken of Cadences, I muſt not omit a Cloſe which is made without either of the forementioned Cadences, and is uſed for a Concluſion to ſome Fancies, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tets, or other grave Muſick; in which the <hi>Baſs</hi> falleth a Fourth or riſeth a Fifth, and part of the final Note is commonly taken into the Deſcant in this manner.</p>
                     <p>I will give one Example of dividing upon it, becauſe, if at <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> any time you play or compoſe Diviſion to a <hi>Through-Baſs</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Ground, you may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily meet with it. I will alſo ſet down a <hi>Long,</hi> or four <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breves</hi> before the Concluding Note; becauſe I have known ſome Beginners apprehend great difficulty in playing upon Notes ſtanding long in the ſame place.</p>
                     <p>Where you ſee any Note with a Tail both upward and downward (as in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Line of the next example,) it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies two Strings ſounding in <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſon;</hi> one being ſtopped and the other open.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52084:29"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Example of a Cloſe without a Cadence</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52084:30"/>
                     <p>I have not diſtinguiſhed the three ſorts of <hi>Diviſion</hi> in this laſt Example, becauſe the <hi>Ground-Notes</hi> ſtanding ſo long in the ſame place, do not admit any diſtinction betwixt <hi>Breaking the Ground</hi> and <hi>Deſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon it. But this which I have ſet down may ſuffice to ſhew you the way of Dividing upon ſuch Notes, albeit their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the ſame place were yet much longer.</p>
                     <p>Although I did ſet, in the former Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, the ſeveral Ways by themſelves, that you might better obſerve how they differ one from another; yet in Playing or Compoſing <hi>Diviſion to a Ground,</hi> we may either continue any one Way (perhaps a whole Strain together) or change from This to That, as frequently as we pleaſe; inſomuch, that ſometimes <hi>part</hi> of the ſame Note is broken in one ſort of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> and <hi>part</hi> of it in another, as you ſee in this Inſtance; In which the <hi>firſt</hi> part of the <hi>Semibreve</hi> in <hi>D,</hi> is divided according to the way of <hi>Breaking the Ground,</hi> and the <hi>later</hi> part of it in the way of <hi>Deſcant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 9.</hi> Of Crochets.</head>
                     <p>HItherto we have treated concerning the Dividing of <hi>Minims, Semibreves,</hi> or longer Notes; which duly conſidered might alſo ſerve for Notes that are ſhorter: But, that I may, as neer as I can, omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which may eaſe or aſſiſt the young Practicioner, I will give ſome Examples upon ſhorter Notes, as <hi>Crochets</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> with ſuch Obſervations as I think requiſite; and firſt, of <hi>Crochets</hi> aſcending and deſcending by degrees.</p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52084:30"/>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>An Example upon Crochets aſcending by Degrees</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Descant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:52084:31"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paradigma Semiminimarum gradatim deſcendentium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Example upon Crochets deſcending by Degrees</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Descant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Having ſhewed you <hi>Crochets</hi> moving by <hi>degrees,</hi> I will now let you ſee them move by <hi>leaps,</hi> in a <hi>Ground</hi> of two Strains.</p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52084:31"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Example of Crochets riſing and falling by Leaps</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Descant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52084:32"/>
                     <p>In this foregoing <hi>Ground</hi> you have all the Intervalls or Diſtances which are in an <hi>Octave;</hi> for, in the firſt Strain you have Thirds falling and Fourths riſing, which include, as the ſame thing, Sixths riſing and Fifths falling. In the ſecond Strain you have on the contrary, Thirds riſing and Fourths falling, which is the ſame with Sixths falling and Fifths riſing. And laſtly, for Sevenths you have Them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded (by their oppoſite <hi>Octaves</hi>) in ſuch Notes as riſe or fall by degrees.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>10.</hi> Of Quavers.</head>
                     <p>IF <hi>Quavers</hi> occur in a <hi>Ground</hi> upon which you are to Play or Compoſe <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion;</hi> you are, firſt, to conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be not the Minute parts of ſome longer Note: as for example, when they move by degrees to make a tranſition to ſome other Note, as in ſuch inſtances as theſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here they ſignifie no more than the plain Notes which you ſee in the Bars next after them; and therefore, if you divide upon ſuch <hi>Quavers,</hi> as you would do upon the ſaid plain Notes, only making your <hi>Diviſion</hi> proceed in a contrary motion to to the <hi>Quavers,</hi> the Muſick may paſs for currant, eſpecially in Playing <hi>ex tempore</hi> to a <hi>Ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But, in caſe you deſire to divide the <hi>Quavers</hi> themſelves, or to Play <hi>Deſcant</hi> or <hi>Mixt Diviſion</hi> upon them, I will ſhew you them according to the Method of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Examples, by riſing and falling by degrees.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:52084:32"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Example upon Quavers Riſing and Falling by Degrees</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The ground <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> The Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Deſcant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Mixt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt variation of this Example, is a little irregular, as to what we have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered of meeting each following Note in the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſon</hi> or <hi>Octave,</hi> for <hi>here</hi> each other <hi>Quaver</hi> is met in a <hi>Second.</hi> But neceſſity or ſhortneſs of Diſſonance renders that excuſable in ſhort Notes which would not be Allowed in longer. For, as <hi>Crochets</hi> ſo broken into <hi>Quavers</hi> are not very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, ſo <hi>Minims</hi> broken into <hi>Crochets</hi> after the ſame manner would be much worſe. But if That Aſcending and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52084:33"/>by degrees conſiſted of <hi>Prick-Notes,</hi> ſucceeded by Notes of the next leſs quan tity; Then, that way of Breaking would be both regular and commendable; as thus,</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Ground <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Broken <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Ground <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Broken</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 11.</hi> Of <hi>b</hi> Flat and Sharp.</head>
                     <p>IF you ask me why I put a <hi>b</hi> flat to that <hi>Quaver</hi> in <hi>B;</hi> I anſwer, becauſe the <hi>Diviſion</hi> deſcends from it to <hi>F</hi> which is flat. Again, in the other part which aſcends, there is a <hi>Quaver</hi> in <hi>F,</hi> made ſharp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Diviſion</hi> aſcends from It to <hi>B,</hi> which is ſharp: Both which are grounded upon the ſame Reaſon; which is, that in <hi>foure Notes aſcending</hi> or <hi>deſcending</hi> by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</hi> we ſeldome exceed the diſtance of a <hi>perfect Fourth,</hi> leſt we produce unto the Ear that harſhneſs which is called <hi>Relation not harmonical:</hi> for though the <hi>leſſer Fourth</hi> be moſt frequent and very agreeable in Muſical progreſſion, yet when both Terms are extended, the Higher being ſharp, and the Lower flat, the diſtance is then a <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone,</hi> which is more by half a Note than a <hi>perfect Fourth;</hi> and therefore when this happens, we commonly alter that which comes firſt in complyance to, (and preparing the Ear for) that which is to follow. And here you may obſerve Three different <hi>Fourths</hi> in <hi>Practical Muſick, viz.</hi> a <hi>Tritone,</hi> or <hi>exceſſive Fourth, Diateſſaron</hi> or <hi>perfect Fourth,</hi> and the <hi>leſſer Fourth</hi> we ſpoke of, which is when the lower Term is ſharp and the higher flat; thus exemplified:</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>As for <hi>Quavers</hi> moving by leaps, I have little to ſay, more than that <hi>Grounds</hi> ought not to conſiſt of Notes ſo quick as <hi>Quavers</hi> in ſuch a movement. But if ſuch Notes ſhould be propoſed, you may ſerve your ſelf by that Example you had of <hi>Crochets;</hi> making them <hi>Quavers,</hi> and the <hi>Quavers</hi> upon them <hi>Semiquavers.</hi> Or, as you ſee in this following Example.</p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52084:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quavers moving by Leaps</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground broken</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Deſcant</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Mixt <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Mixt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It now only remains that I give you ſome little aſſiſtance, by taking you (as it were) by the Hand, and leading you into the eaſieſt way of Playing <hi>Ex tempore</hi> to a <hi>Ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt, you are to make choice of ſome <hi>Ground</hi> conſiſting of <hi>Semibreves</hi> or <hi>Minims,</hi> or a mixture of theſe two: for ſuch ought <hi>Grounds</hi> to be, which are propoſed to be Play'd upon at ſight.</p>
                     <p>Next, you ought to be provided of ten, twelve, or more points of <hi>Diviſion</hi> (the more the better) each conſiſting of a <hi>Semibreve</hi> or <hi>Minim,</hi> which you may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate to the firſt Note or Notes of your <hi>Ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Being thus prepared, take one of the ſaid Points, and apply it firſt to One Note, and then to another, and ſo through the whole <hi>Ground.</hi> When you can do this, take another Point, and do the like with it, and ſo one after another ſo many as you pleaſe.</p>
                     <p>I will here for your eaſe and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment furniſh you with a <hi>Ground,</hi> and alſo with ſome <hi>Points;</hi> to which you may add infinite more at your pleaſure.</p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52084:34"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Ground <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> points</hi> 
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let us now take ſome of theſe <hi>Points</hi> and apply them to the precedent <hi>Ground,</hi> that you may by Example ſee how they are to be carried on.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52084:34"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Example for carrying on a point upon a Ground</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52084:35"/>
                     <p>This driving or carrying on of a <hi>Point,</hi> doth much eaſe the Invention, which hath no further trouble, ſo long as the <hi>Point</hi> is continued, but to place and apply it to the ſeveral Notes of the <hi>Ground:</hi> Beſides, it renders the <hi>Diviſion</hi> more uniform and more delightful alſo; provided you do not cloy the Ear with too much repetition of the ſame thing; which is eaſily avoyded by a little variation, as you ſee I have done in carrying on ſome of the foregoing <hi>Points,</hi> Alſo you have liberty to change your <hi>Point</hi> though in the middle or in any other part of the <hi>Ground:</hi> or you may mingle one <hi>Point</hi> with another, as beſt ſhall pleaſe your fancy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 12.</hi> Concerning ordering of Diviſion.</head>
                     <p>WHen you are to Play <hi>Diviſion</hi> to a <hi>Ground,</hi> I would have you, in the firſt place, to Play over the <hi>Ground</hi> it ſelf, plainly and diſtinctly; for theſe reaſons: 1. That others may hear what Notes you divide upon. 2. That your ſelf may be better poſſeſſed of the <hi>Ayre</hi> of the <hi>Ground,</hi> in caſe you know it not before. 3. That he who Plays the <hi>Ground</hi> unto you may better perceive the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of <hi>Time.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ground</hi> being Played over, you may then break it into <hi>Crochets</hi> and <hi>Quavers;</hi> or Play ſome neat peece of ſlow <hi>Deſcant</hi> to it, which you pleaſe. If your <hi>Ground</hi> conſiſt of two or three <hi>Strains,</hi> you may do by the ſecond or third, as you did by the firſt.</p>
                     <p>This done, and your <hi>Ground</hi> beginning over again, you may then break it into <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> of a quicker motion, driving on ſome <hi>Point</hi> or <hi>Points</hi> as hath been ſhewed.</p>
                     <p>When you have proſecuted that manner of Play ſo long as you think fitting, and ſhewed ſome command of Hand; you may then fall off to ſlower <hi>Deſcant</hi> or <hi>Binding-Notes,</hi> as you ſee cauſe; Playing alſo ſometimes loud or ſoft, to expreſs Humour and draw on Attention.</p>
                     <p>After this you may begin to Play ſome <hi>Skipping Diviſion;</hi> or <hi>Points,</hi> or <hi>Tripla's,</hi> or what your preſent fancy or invention ſhall prompt you to, changing ſtill from one variety to another; for variety it is which chiefly pleaſeth: The beſt <hi>Diviſion</hi> in the world, ſtil continued, would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come tedious to the Hearer; and therefore you muſt ſo place and diſpoſe your <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> that the change of it from one kind to another may ſtill beget a new attention: And this is generally to be obſerved, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your <hi>Ground</hi> conſiſt of one or more <hi>Strains,</hi> or be a <hi>Continued Ground;</hi> of which I muſt alſo ſpeak a little.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52084:35"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 13.</hi> Of a Continued Ground.</head>
                     <p>A <hi>Continued Ground</hi> uſed for Playing or Making <hi>Diviſion</hi> upon, is (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly) the <hi>Through-Baſs</hi> of ſome <hi>Motet</hi> or <hi>Madrigal,</hi> propoſed or ſelected for that purpoſe. This, after you have played two or three <hi>Semibreves</hi> of it plain, to let the Organiſt know your meaſure; you may begin to divide, according to your fancy, or the former Inſtructions, until you come near ſome <hi>Cadence</hi> or <hi>Cloſe,</hi> where I would have you ſhew ſome Agility of Hand. There, if you pleaſe, you may reſt a <hi>Minim,</hi> two or three, letting him that Plays the <hi>Ground</hi> go on: and then come in with ſome <hi>Point:</hi> after which you may fall to <hi>Deſcant, Mixt Diviſion, Tripla's,</hi> or what you pleaſe. In this manner, Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes ſwift Notes, ſometimes ſlow; changing from This or that ſort of <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> as may beſt produce Variety, you may carry on the reſt of the <hi>Ground;</hi> and if you have any thing more excellent than other, reſerve it for the Concluſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 14.</hi> Of Compoſing Diviſion for one Viol to a Ground.</head>
                     <p>WHen you compoſe <hi>Diviſion</hi> to a <hi>Ground,</hi> endevour to make it eaſie for the Hand: for, of things equally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent as to Muſick, That is always to be preferred, which is more eaſie to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Hence we may conclude, that no man is ſit to Compoſe <hi>Diviſion</hi> to a <hi>Ground</hi> (how great a Maſter in Muſick ſoever he be) unleſs he know the neck of the Inſtrument, and the Method of Finger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing belonging unto it.</p>
                     <p>This is all I have to ſay concerning <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> for one <hi>Viol;</hi> more than that I would have you peruſe the <hi>Diviſions</hi> which other men have made upon <hi>Grounds;</hi> as thoſe of Mr. <hi>Henry Butler,</hi> Mr. <hi>Daniel Norcome,</hi> and divers other excellent men of this our Nation, who (hitherto) have had the preheminence for this particular Inſtrument; obſerving and noting in their <hi>Diviſions,</hi> what you find beſt worthy to be imitated.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 15.</hi> Of two Viols Playing together <hi>ex tempore</hi> to a Ground.</head>
                     <p>AFter this Diſcourſe of <hi>Diviſion</hi> for One <hi>Viol,</hi> I ſuppoſe it will not be unſeaſonable to ſpeak ſomething of Two <hi>Viols</hi> Playing together upon a <hi>Ground;</hi> in which kind of Muſick, I have had ſome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52084:36"/>experimental knowledg; and therefore will deliver it in ſuch order and manner as I have known the practice of it; referring the Improvement thereof to further expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, let the <hi>Ground</hi> be prick'd down in three ſeveral Papers; One for him who Plays upon the <hi>Organ</hi> or <hi>Harpſechord:</hi> The other two for them that Play upon the two <hi>Viols:</hi> which, for order and brevity, we will diſtinguiſh by three Letters; <hi>viz. A.</hi> for <hi>Organiſt, B.</hi> for the <hi>firſt Baſs,</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> for the <hi>ſecond.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Each of theſe having the ſame <hi>Ground</hi> before him, they may all three begin to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> Playing the <hi>Ground,</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> Deſcanting to it, in ſlow Notes, or ſuch as may ſute the beginning of the Muſick: This done, let <hi>C.</hi> Play the <hi>Ground,</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> Deſcant to it, as the other had done before, but with ſome little variation. If the <hi>Ground</hi> conſiſt of two Strains, the like may be done in the ſecond: One <hi>Viol</hi> ſtill Playing the <hi>Ground</hi> whileſt the other Deſcants or Divides upon it.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ground</hi> thus Play'd over, <hi>C.</hi> may begin again, and Play a Strain of quicker <hi>Diviſion;</hi> which ended, let <hi>B.</hi> anſwer the ſame with another ſomething like it, but of a little more lofty Ayre: for the better performance whereof, if there be any difference in the Hands or Inventions, I would have the better Invention <hi>lead,</hi> but the more able Hand ſtill <hi>follow,</hi> that the Muſick may not ſeem to flacceſs or leſſen, but rather increaſe in the performance.</p>
                     <p>When the <hi>Viols</hi> have thus (as it were) Vied and Revied one to the other, <hi>A.</hi> if he have ability of Hand, may, upon a ſign given him, put in his Strain of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion;</hi> the two <hi>Viols</hi> Playing one of them the <hi>Ground,</hi> and the other <hi>ſlow</hi> Deſcant to it. <hi>A.</hi> having ſiniſhed his Strain, a reply thereto may be made, firſt by one <hi>Viol,</hi> and then by the other.</p>
                     <p>Having anſwered one another in that ſame manner ſo long as they think ſit, the two <hi>Viols</hi> may divide a Strain Both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In which doing, let <hi>B.</hi> break the <hi>Ground,</hi> by moving into the <hi>Octave</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or downward, and returning from thence either to his own Note, or to meet the next Note in the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſon</hi> or <hi>Octave.</hi> By this means, <hi>C.</hi> knowing <hi>B</hi>'s motion, he knows alſo how to avoyd running into the ſame, and therefore will move into the Third or Fifth, (or Sixth where it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired) meeting each ſucceeding Note in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52084:36"/>ſome one of the ſaid Concords, until he come to the Cloſe; where he may (after he has divided the Binding) meet the Cloſe Note in the <hi>Octave;</hi> which Directions well obſerved, two <hi>Viols</hi> may move in <hi>Extemporary</hi> Diviſion a whole Strain together, without any remarkable claſhing in the Conſecution of <hi>Fifths</hi> or <hi>Eighths.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When they have proceeded thus far; <hi>C.</hi> may begin ſome Point of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> of the length of a <hi>Breve</hi> or <hi>Semibreve,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſaid word, that <hi>B.</hi> may know his intentions: which ended, let <hi>B.</hi> anſwer the ſame upon the ſucceeding Note or Notes to the like quantity of Time; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it in that manner, one after another, ſo long as they pleaſe. This done, they may betake themſelves to ſome other Point of a different length, which will produce a new variety.</p>
                     <p>This conteſt in <hi>Breves, Semibreves,</hi> or <hi>Minims</hi> being ended, they may give the Signe to <hi>A.</hi> if (as I ſaid) he have ability of Hand, that he may begin his Point, as they had done one to another; which Point may be anſwered by the <hi>Viols,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſingly or joyntly; if jointly, it muſt be done according to the former Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Dividing together; Playing ſtill <hi>ſlow</hi> Notes and <hi>ſoft,</hi> whileſt the <hi>Organiſt</hi> Divides; for that Part which Divides ſhould always be heard lowdeſt.</p>
                     <p>When this is done, both <hi>Viols</hi> may Play another Strain together, either in quick or ſlow Notes, which they pleaſe; and if the Muſick be not yet ſpun out to a ſufficient length, they may begin to Play <hi>Tripla</hi>'s and Proportions, anſwering each other either in whole Strains or parcels; and after that, joyn together in a Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Strain of <hi>Quick</hi> Diviſion; with which they may conclude; or elſe with a Strain of ſlow and ſweet Notes, according as may beſt ſute the circumſtance of time and place.</p>
                     <p>I have known this kind of <hi>Extemporary</hi> Muſick, ſometimes (when it was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Hands accuſtomed to Play toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) paſs off with greater applauſe, than thoſe Diviſions which had been moſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly compoſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>§ 16.</hi> Of Compoſing Diviſions of Two or Three Parts.</head>
                     <p>IN Compoſing Diviſion for <hi>two Baſs Viols,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Two Baſſes</note> you may follow the forementioned me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, making ſometimes This, ſometimes That <hi>Part</hi> move above or below: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times anſwering one the other in Points,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52084:37"/>joyned together in Diviſion; ſometimes in <hi>ſiow,</hi> ſometimes in <hi>quick</hi> Motions, ſuch as may beſt produce Variety: but after their anſwering one another in Points, I would always have them joyn together in ſome lofty Strain of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> with which, or with ſome ſlow and pleaſing <hi>Deſcant</hi> you may conclude your Compoſition.</p>
                     <p>If you make <hi>Diviſion</hi> for <hi>two Trebles,</hi> both muſt be in the way of <hi>Deſcant</hi> to the <hi>Ground:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Two tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> So, that (the <hi>Ground</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) the Compoſition is Three diſtinct Parts. When the <hi>Trebles</hi> move together, their moſt natural paſſage is in <hi>Thirds</hi> one to the other; ſometimes in <hi>Sixths</hi> or a mixture with other <hi>Concords,</hi> but ſtill ſuch as have relation to the <hi>Ground.</hi> As for their anſwering one another in <hi>Points;</hi> their ſeveral Motions and Changes, in order to Variety; the ſame is underſtood as of the former.</p>
                     <p>In Compoſing for a <hi>Treble</hi> and <hi>Baſs,</hi> you are to conſider the nature and compaſs of either Part,<note place="margin">Treble and Baſs.</note> framing your <hi>Diviſion</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto; which, in the higher Part will be <hi>Deſcant;</hi> in the lower, a more frequent <hi>Breaking</hi> of the <hi>Ground.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſame regard, to the nature of the Parts,<note place="margin">Two Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and a Baſs. Two Baſſes and a Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Three Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> muſt be had in Compoſing for <hi>two Trebles</hi> and a <hi>Baſs,</hi> or for <hi>two Baſſes</hi> and <hi>one Treble.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In <hi>Diviſions</hi> made for <hi>three Baſſes,</hi> every <hi>Viol</hi> acts the <hi>Treble, Baſs,</hi> or <hi>Inward</hi> Part, by turns. But here you are to take notice, that <hi>Diviſions</hi> of Three Parts, are not uſually made upon <hi>Grounds;</hi> but rather Compoſed in the manner of <hi>Fancies;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning commonly with ſome <hi>Fuge,</hi> and then falling into Points of <hi>Diviſion;</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering one another; ſometimes two a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one, and ſometimes all engaged at once in a conteſt of <hi>Diviſion:</hi> But (after all) ending commonly in grave and harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Muſick.</p>
                     <p>Howbeit, if, after each <hi>Fancie</hi> there follow an <hi>Ayre</hi> (which will produce a pleaſant Variety) the <hi>Baſſes</hi> of Theſe conſiſting of two ſhort Strains, differ not much from the nature of <hi>Grounds.</hi> Theſe <hi>Ayres</hi> or <hi>Almains</hi> begin like other <hi>Conſort Ayres;</hi> after which the Strains are repeated in divers Variations, one Part anſwering another, and ſometimes joyning together in <hi>Division,</hi> as formerly mention'd.</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:52084:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>In theſe ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Diviſion</hi> of <hi>two</hi> and <hi>three Parts,</hi> my ſelf, amonſt others more eminent, have made divers Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, which perhaps might be uſeful to young Muſicians, either for their Imitation or Practice: but the Charge of Printing <hi>Diviſions</hi> (as I have experienced in the <hi>Cuts</hi> of the <hi>Examples</hi> in this preſent Book) doth make that kind of Muſick leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable. Howbeit, if you deſire writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Copies of that ſort, (a thing moſt neceſſary for thoſe who intend to Compoſe ſuch like themſelves) none has done ſo much in that kind, as the ever Famous and moſt Excellent Compoſer, in all ſorts of Modern Muſick, Mr. <hi>John Jenkins.</hi> And here might I mention (were it not out of the rode of my deſign) divers Eminent men in this our Kingdom; who, in their various and excellent Compoſitions, eſpecially for Inſtruments, have (in my opinion) far out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done thoſe Nations ſo much cry'd up for their excellency in Muſick: but my naming them would ſignifie little, they being ſufficiently known and honoured by their own Works; neither had I taken upon me to nominate any particular perſon, had it not been upon the neceſſary accompt of <hi>Diviſion-Muſick,</hi> the peculiar Subject of our now ended Diſcourſe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="exercises">
            <pb facs="tcp:52084:38"/>
            <head>Minuritiones, Tyronum exercitationi, accommodoe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Divisions for the practice of Learners</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Prolusio <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Prolusio <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52084:38"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Prelude <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Prelude <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Prelude <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52084:39"/>
            <p> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The Ground <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52084:39"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52084:40"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52084:40"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:52084:41"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:52084:41"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:52084:42"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:52084:42"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:52084:43"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:52084:43"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:52084:44"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:52084:44"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:52084:45"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:52084:45"/> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
